<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-05T08:44:27-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Making the map match the territory</title><entry><title type="html">Leaving Dr. Bill</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal/2021/03/05/leaving-dr-bill.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leaving Dr. Bill" /><published>2021-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal/2021/03/05/leaving-dr-bill</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal/2021/03/05/leaving-dr-bill.html">&lt;p&gt;In December 2013, my two partners and I started &lt;a href=&quot;www.dr-bill.ca&quot;&gt;Dr. Bill&lt;/a&gt; - a medical billing service for Canadian physicians. In October 2019, Dr. Bill was acquired by &lt;a href=&quot;www.rbcventures.ca&quot;&gt;RBC Ventures&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is my last on this journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the experience and all the people who chose to be part of it with us and all those who helped us out along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reflecting on this experience and thinking about the future, I was, uncharacteristically, inspired to write a little poem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Shut Up &amp;amp; Build&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three fools in a box,&lt;br/&gt;
Wandering in an unknown field,&lt;br/&gt;
Guided by a single direction:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scraping by on ramen noodles,&lt;br/&gt;
Handing out fliers on the street,&lt;br/&gt;
Knowing there&amp;rsquo;s only one way forward:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success came in stages,&lt;br/&gt;
For doctor dollars we had greed.&lt;br/&gt;
Still only one way to get it:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First enchanted by nephrologists,&lt;br/&gt;
Doing periodic hemodialysis,&lt;br/&gt;
Confused by &amp;lsquo;anaesthesiology&amp;rsquo;,&lt;br/&gt;
Distracted by endocrinologists,&lt;br/&gt;
We stumbled upon internal med,&lt;br/&gt;
And their strange rules to bill.&lt;br/&gt;
They reminded us once again:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramen noodles were replaced,&lt;br/&gt;
By dollar slice pizza.&lt;br/&gt;
Very soon we could even,&lt;br/&gt;
Travel to Ibiza.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users rolled in bit by bit&lt;br/&gt;
And we set our sights higher.&lt;br/&gt;
No longer did we have to&lt;br/&gt;
Walk and handout fliers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew not what we were doing,&lt;br/&gt;
whether it was right or wrong.&lt;br/&gt;
We just knew it was gruelling,&lt;br/&gt;
the road appeared too long.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to grow faster,&lt;br/&gt;
so we took on more funding.&lt;br/&gt;
But that was a disaster,&lt;br/&gt;
it meant the fun was ending.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HabitStack, OKRs, &amp;ldquo;strategy&amp;rdquo;,&lt;br/&gt;
focusing on the wrong things.&lt;br/&gt;
Forgetting the cardinal rule:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then handing over the reigns,&lt;br/&gt;
Thinking the grass was greener.&lt;br/&gt;
With a company from the gilded age,&lt;br/&gt;
Customers would be keener.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But no amount of experience,&lt;br/&gt;
Or fancy management degrees,&lt;br/&gt;
Make up for the one true path:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to part ways,&lt;br/&gt;
The box has gotten too big.&lt;br/&gt;
We leave you with exhortations,&lt;br/&gt;
to avoid the mistakes we did.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From management frameworks &lt;br/&gt;
nor deep market analysis,&lt;br/&gt;
There is naught to be learned&lt;br/&gt;
About billing hemodialysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The customer has your answers,&lt;br/&gt;
And once you have what you need,&lt;br/&gt;
Don’t forget that noble decree:&lt;br/&gt;
Shut up and build.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">In December 2013, my two partners and I started Dr. Bill - a medical billing service for Canadian physicians. In October 2019, Dr. Bill was acquired by RBC Ventures. Today is my last on this journey. I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the experience and all the people who chose to be part of it with us and all those who helped us out along the way. While reflecting on this experience and thinking about the future, I was, uncharacteristically, inspired to write a little poem. Shut Up &amp;amp; Build Three fools in a box, Wandering in an unknown field, Guided by a single direction: Shut up and build Scraping by on ramen noodles, Handing out fliers on the street, Knowing there&amp;rsquo;s only one way forward: Shut up and build Success came in stages, For doctor dollars we had greed. Still only one way to get it: Shut up and build. First enchanted by nephrologists, Doing periodic hemodialysis, Confused by &amp;lsquo;anaesthesiology&amp;rsquo;, Distracted by endocrinologists, We stumbled upon internal med, And their strange rules to bill. They reminded us once again: Shut up and build. Ramen noodles were replaced, By dollar slice pizza. Very soon we could even, Travel to Ibiza. Users rolled in bit by bit And we set our sights higher. No longer did we have to Walk and handout fliers. We knew not what we were doing, whether it was right or wrong. We just knew it was gruelling, the road appeared too long. We wanted to grow faster, so we took on more funding. But that was a disaster, it meant the fun was ending. HabitStack, OKRs, &amp;ldquo;strategy&amp;rdquo;, focusing on the wrong things. Forgetting the cardinal rule: Shut up and build. Then handing over the reigns, Thinking the grass was greener. With a company from the gilded age, Customers would be keener. But no amount of experience, Or fancy management degrees, Make up for the one true path: Shut up and build. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to part ways, The box has gotten too big. We leave you with exhortations, to avoid the mistakes we did. From management frameworks nor deep market analysis, There is naught to be learned About billing hemodialysis. The customer has your answers, And once you have what you need, Don’t forget that noble decree: Shut up and build.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">People Ponderings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2021/02/15/people-ponderings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="People Ponderings" /><published>2021-02-15T12:51:37-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T12:51:37-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2021/02/15/people-ponderings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2021/02/15/people-ponderings.html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last several years, I had two individuals in my life whose association significantly degraded my quality of life and caused much suffering. In both cases, these individuals were very personable. In both cases there were red flags early on that I ignored. Probably, these people were quite far on the narcisism spectrum, if not clinically so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a few lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned mostly from the misfortune of knowing these two individuals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrity is really the most important thing.&lt;/strong&gt; If you smell lack of integrity in someone – no matter how small – run. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing good that can come out of any relationship with someone without integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The best liars lie to themselves first.&lt;/strong&gt; Some people are too wrapped up in stories they tell themselves to be able to see if they&amp;rsquo;re behaving without integrity. Those are the hardest people to read a lack of integrity in, because they always seem genuine. Assess the behaviour apart from emotion. Honest liars can trigger sympathy even when it&amp;rsquo;s completely unwarranted by their behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-elevation is the biggest tell.&lt;/strong&gt; Elevating oneself and degrading others are two sides of the same coin, and those who do one often do the other, too. Some people act as if they have higher social status than they actually do. One of the most obvious ways to do this is unsolicited teaching. The fool will deem himself worthy to teach others anything, no matter how little he knows. Someone who is skilled and wise is also typically humble enough to not give unsolicited advice. Pretending like they&amp;rsquo;re in a position to teach someone is a red flag, but that&amp;rsquo;s only one example of self-elevation. Another might be giving praise for things that they&amp;rsquo;re in no position to judge, or giving praise in such a way that implies the praiseworthy action was taken to impress them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laziness is another tell.&lt;/strong&gt; Having integrity and not lying to oneself can sometimes be difficult. When the going gets tough, some people weave narratives for themselves to justify taking the easy way. We all do it, but some of us at some point develop antidotes to our own bullshit, and we start keeping our selfish inner voice in check. Some people never develop this inner voice, which means they have no antidote to their own bullshit. This also means, they have no antidote to taking the easy way out of anything. Be on the lookout for laziness. It often comes with other character flaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Observe actions and heavily discount words.&lt;/strong&gt; Both of the (pseudo-)narcisists that I know are obsessed with perception management. They talk about their own accomplishments and work, often with skillful subtlety, to impress you. If they think you don&amp;rsquo;t perceive them well, they will go to great lengths to try to change that perception. This often involves a lot of verbal persuasion or empty gestures like gift-buying – anything but changing their anti-social behaviour. Once you observe their actions closely, however, major discrepancies start to emerge. As a famous verse of Persian poetry says: &amp;ldquo;Good perfume is the one you can smell, not what the perfumer advertises.&amp;rdquo; People who are accomplished or those who work hard don&amp;rsquo;t need to talk about it, nor do those who are kind and compassionate. Ignore people&amp;rsquo;s words about themselves almost compeletely, and try to assess their character solely on their actions. If the words have any value, it&amp;rsquo;ll be in highlighting a discrepancy with the actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really difficult to learn some lessons except through direct, first-hand experience. Others may have tried to teach me these lessons but without the experience of dealing with these probable narcisists, I could have never understood. I suppose in that way, I have to be grateful for them for building up my asshole-immunity. While I&amp;rsquo;m now on high alert for these behaviour traits, an open question is my mind is how to react to these people. I don&amp;rsquo;t think a zero-tolerance policy is tenable – after all, we&amp;rsquo;re all somewhere on a spectrum with regards to any behaviour. I think sometimes, one needs a &amp;lsquo;management&amp;rsquo; policy, rather than an &amp;lsquo;avoidance&amp;rsquo; policy, but it&amp;rsquo;s key to detect these personalities early and, even if one can&amp;rsquo;t avoid the individuals completely, avoid situations where too much rides on relationships with these individuals.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">Over the last several years, I had two individuals in my life whose association significantly degraded my quality of life and caused much suffering. In both cases, these individuals were very personable. In both cases there were red flags early on that I ignored. Probably, these people were quite far on the narcisism spectrum, if not clinically so. These are a few lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learned mostly from the misfortune of knowing these two individuals: Integrity is really the most important thing. If you smell lack of integrity in someone – no matter how small – run. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing good that can come out of any relationship with someone without integrity. The best liars lie to themselves first. Some people are too wrapped up in stories they tell themselves to be able to see if they&amp;rsquo;re behaving without integrity. Those are the hardest people to read a lack of integrity in, because they always seem genuine. Assess the behaviour apart from emotion. Honest liars can trigger sympathy even when it&amp;rsquo;s completely unwarranted by their behaviour. Self-elevation is the biggest tell. Elevating oneself and degrading others are two sides of the same coin, and those who do one often do the other, too. Some people act as if they have higher social status than they actually do. One of the most obvious ways to do this is unsolicited teaching. The fool will deem himself worthy to teach others anything, no matter how little he knows. Someone who is skilled and wise is also typically humble enough to not give unsolicited advice. Pretending like they&amp;rsquo;re in a position to teach someone is a red flag, but that&amp;rsquo;s only one example of self-elevation. Another might be giving praise for things that they&amp;rsquo;re in no position to judge, or giving praise in such a way that implies the praiseworthy action was taken to impress them. Laziness is another tell. Having integrity and not lying to oneself can sometimes be difficult. When the going gets tough, some people weave narratives for themselves to justify taking the easy way. We all do it, but some of us at some point develop antidotes to our own bullshit, and we start keeping our selfish inner voice in check. Some people never develop this inner voice, which means they have no antidote to their own bullshit. This also means, they have no antidote to taking the easy way out of anything. Be on the lookout for laziness. It often comes with other character flaws. Observe actions and heavily discount words. Both of the (pseudo-)narcisists that I know are obsessed with perception management. They talk about their own accomplishments and work, often with skillful subtlety, to impress you. If they think you don&amp;rsquo;t perceive them well, they will go to great lengths to try to change that perception. This often involves a lot of verbal persuasion or empty gestures like gift-buying – anything but changing their anti-social behaviour. Once you observe their actions closely, however, major discrepancies start to emerge. As a famous verse of Persian poetry says: &amp;ldquo;Good perfume is the one you can smell, not what the perfumer advertises.&amp;rdquo; People who are accomplished or those who work hard don&amp;rsquo;t need to talk about it, nor do those who are kind and compassionate. Ignore people&amp;rsquo;s words about themselves almost compeletely, and try to assess their character solely on their actions. If the words have any value, it&amp;rsquo;ll be in highlighting a discrepancy with the actions. It&amp;rsquo;s really difficult to learn some lessons except through direct, first-hand experience. Others may have tried to teach me these lessons but without the experience of dealing with these probable narcisists, I could have never understood. I suppose in that way, I have to be grateful for them for building up my asshole-immunity. While I&amp;rsquo;m now on high alert for these behaviour traits, an open question is my mind is how to react to these people. I don&amp;rsquo;t think a zero-tolerance policy is tenable – after all, we&amp;rsquo;re all somewhere on a spectrum with regards to any behaviour. I think sometimes, one needs a &amp;lsquo;management&amp;rsquo; policy, rather than an &amp;lsquo;avoidance&amp;rsquo; policy, but it&amp;rsquo;s key to detect these personalities early and, even if one can&amp;rsquo;t avoid the individuals completely, avoid situations where too much rides on relationships with these individuals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Election Reflection</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/11/10/election-reflection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Election Reflection" /><published>2020-11-10T08:27:19-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-10T08:27:19-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/11/10/election-reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/11/10/election-reflection.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2016, I was happy when Donald Trump won the election. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much that I liked him, it was more that everyone else was so repugnant. Sure, Trump lied, but he was transparent in his lying, whereas regular politicians lie and sanctimoniously pretend otherwise. Moreover, by 2016 I had paid attention to politics long enough to know that on certain key issues, the two parties in the US were in total agreement and thus the population would never get an opportunity to vote for a true alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From all this I deduced that the president actually didn&amp;rsquo;t have much power at all. I imagined that it was mostly the unelected, entrenched bureaucrats of the deep state that would make the key decisions and present the president with a limited range of options on any given issue. This is the same sense in which Eisenhower referred to the military-industrial complex. I think it is a correct but incomplete picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump certainly had the intended effect of being a disruptor. Had voters had any other means of making themselves and their disillusionment with traditional politics heard, I think it would be preferrable. Unfortunately, Trump was the only option available, and he had to be locked in for four years and preside over a pandemic, as bad luck would have it. But disruption did occur. History will look on the Trump presidency as a pivotal moment for the two American parties, which will now remake themselves in a new image. It is to be determined what that image will be for each party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to Trump, however, the progressive wing of American politics and society completely lost its mind. Not only have they not backed off from the &amp;ldquo;basket of deplorables&amp;rdquo; comments, they have doubled and tripled down in the last four years. Trump supporters are routinely caricatured by the left as racist, sexist, homophobic hicks, their concerns and motivations not to be taken seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American media, with few exceptions deeply steeped in the progressive agenda, have completely lost all credibility as neutral conveyors of facts. During the last four years, we have gone from one manufactured Trump outrage to another, and one after another, they proved to be of no substance whatsoever. We now know that there was no Russian interference, that Cambridge Analytica was mostly a scam, that Trump did denounce white supremacy on numerous occasions, among many other daily, weekly, monthly scandals that have now been forgotten. Journalistic standards were sacrificed at the altar of dethroning Trump. Unverified and wildly exaggerated stories of unproven (and later disproven) scandals abound in the media coverage of American politics in the last four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, not only did Donald Trump prove to be an utterly incompetent, sociopathic narcissist and fool, but the GOP showed a spinelessness in checking his power that is unbecoming and unprecendented even for the slimiest career politician. The most atrocious showing, obviously, has been in the response to the pandemic. America was at war for nearly 20 years because Osama bin Laden killed 3000 people. But in 2020, two hundred thousand have perished and we&amp;rsquo;re supposed to accept it as an inevitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump&amp;rsquo;s incompetence and repugnant presentation should have made this election an easy win for Democrats. It was anything but. The GOP will most likely retain control of the senate, and the Democratic majority in the house will shrink. In other words, the American voter has fired an incompetent narcissist but also emphatically rejected the agenda of his enemies. In this way, I think this election showed not only that American democracy is working but that it&amp;rsquo;s thriving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the bull in the China shop is gone, the two parties have a chance to remake themselves and their policies for the future. Unfortunately, I think Democrats have already made up their minds in this regard. For the last four years, they have hallucinated a battle between the forces of good and evil, with themselves cast as a hero going up against a white supremacist tyrant. They have shown in the process that they understand neither racism, nor tyranny. I, for one, have no confidence that they will see the results of the election as anything other than victory. They will not learn a single lesson from the fact that after four years of screaming about Trump being racist and bigotted, he got more votes from women, minorities, immigrant and LGBTQ communities than any Republican in recent history. The crazy wing of progressives, the intersectionalists, the postmodernists, the identitarians, and the critical race theorists, may have an opportunity to run amok with the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Republicans, however, have an opportunity to cast themselves as the party of the working people of all backgrounds. This election has shown that the traditional notion of immigrants being by default Democrat voters is clearly untrue. I, for one, think immigrants tend to come to Western countries, and America in particular, for the same promises that America makes in its marketing. It is the land of opportunity and the place where you can succeed if you work hard, regardless of who you are. Progressives can scream all they want about inequality and try to recast American history with bigotry at its core. I think immigrants know better than anyone that this is nonsense, and Republicans have a chance to redraw the traditional lines of who their base is. I hope they take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like 2016, this election has left people asking &amp;ldquo;how could 70M people still vote for Trump!?&amp;rdquo;. Let me offer two silver linings to the Trump administration that I&amp;rsquo;m not optimistic a Biden administration will get right: pushing back on the woke movement, and being hawkish on China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single best thing Donald Trump has done in the last four years, as far as I&amp;rsquo;m concerned, is to sign an executive order banning critical race theory-based diversity and inclusion training in government and government contractors. Critical race theory is an inane and dangerous theory that puts people&amp;rsquo;s racial identity, as opposed to their individual character, at the core of their worth as people. Since the killing of George Floyd, critical theorists, like Robyn DeAngelo to name just one example, have been raking in big sums of cash delivering speeches and training seminars, where they tell their audience such nonsense as all white people are innately racist, or that white supremacy is at the core of western civilization. Outside of the novel coronavirus, this strain of thought is now the most dangerous virus sweeping across western society, and it&amp;rsquo;s one virus that the Trump administration has taken at least nominal action on. It&amp;rsquo;s doubtful that a Biden administration will get this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, traditional neoliberal politics and bipartisan support for globalization, precluded presidents before Trump from seeing US-China relations for what it really was: not as a way for the US to export democracy, but as a way for China to export its authoritarianism. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to imply that Trump&amp;rsquo;s hostile stance on China was principled or reasoned out in any way. That would be giving him too much credit. However, it had positive effects and was validated even more by the pandemic, where Americans realized exactly how dependent they were on a not-so-friendly foreign power. Pre-Trump politics put globalization and free trade as the top priority in relation with China, to the detriment of a long-term national security or geopolitical strategy. That free trade stance has not been reciprocated by China, and it has been exploited to export Chinese authorianism to the west. Many people don&amp;rsquo;t realize, for example, how easily Chinese censorship extends beyond Chinese borders. To name one trivial example, scripts for Holywood movies have to be pre-approved by the CCP if the studio has a chance of screening it in China. Effectively, that means none of us get to see a film that may draw the ire of &lt;strike&gt;Winnie the Poo&lt;/strike&gt; Xi Jinping. I&amp;rsquo;m a free-market capitalist, but even I, in this case, see a need for government intervention. Will a Biden administration take on this task, or will it revert to the safety of well-known, but ineffective, policy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is there really is a need to make America great again. Ironically, that need is a lot more severe today than it was four years ago, but to get here took a concerted effort. The pathologies of Donald Trump, American media, and the radical elements of the left wing all conspired to put American society in a four year psychosis. The traditional ways of America&amp;rsquo;s two parties are no longer adequate to meet the needs of its electorate  at home or internationally. The gargantuan task facing the next president is to not just heal the patient but to set it up to thrive in a new world where continued American dominance is far from guaranteed and ideologies opposing core principles of liberal democracy are on the rise both domestically and internationally. Let&amp;rsquo;s wish him well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">In 2016, I was happy when Donald Trump won the election. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much that I liked him, it was more that everyone else was so repugnant. Sure, Trump lied, but he was transparent in his lying, whereas regular politicians lie and sanctimoniously pretend otherwise. Moreover, by 2016 I had paid attention to politics long enough to know that on certain key issues, the two parties in the US were in total agreement and thus the population would never get an opportunity to vote for a true alternative. From all this I deduced that the president actually didn&amp;rsquo;t have much power at all. I imagined that it was mostly the unelected, entrenched bureaucrats of the deep state that would make the key decisions and present the president with a limited range of options on any given issue. This is the same sense in which Eisenhower referred to the military-industrial complex. I think it is a correct but incomplete picture. Trump certainly had the intended effect of being a disruptor. Had voters had any other means of making themselves and their disillusionment with traditional politics heard, I think it would be preferrable. Unfortunately, Trump was the only option available, and he had to be locked in for four years and preside over a pandemic, as bad luck would have it. But disruption did occur. History will look on the Trump presidency as a pivotal moment for the two American parties, which will now remake themselves in a new image. It is to be determined what that image will be for each party. In response to Trump, however, the progressive wing of American politics and society completely lost its mind. Not only have they not backed off from the &amp;ldquo;basket of deplorables&amp;rdquo; comments, they have doubled and tripled down in the last four years. Trump supporters are routinely caricatured by the left as racist, sexist, homophobic hicks, their concerns and motivations not to be taken seriously. American media, with few exceptions deeply steeped in the progressive agenda, have completely lost all credibility as neutral conveyors of facts. During the last four years, we have gone from one manufactured Trump outrage to another, and one after another, they proved to be of no substance whatsoever. We now know that there was no Russian interference, that Cambridge Analytica was mostly a scam, that Trump did denounce white supremacy on numerous occasions, among many other daily, weekly, monthly scandals that have now been forgotten. Journalistic standards were sacrificed at the altar of dethroning Trump. Unverified and wildly exaggerated stories of unproven (and later disproven) scandals abound in the media coverage of American politics in the last four years. At the same time, not only did Donald Trump prove to be an utterly incompetent, sociopathic narcissist and fool, but the GOP showed a spinelessness in checking his power that is unbecoming and unprecendented even for the slimiest career politician. The most atrocious showing, obviously, has been in the response to the pandemic. America was at war for nearly 20 years because Osama bin Laden killed 3000 people. But in 2020, two hundred thousand have perished and we&amp;rsquo;re supposed to accept it as an inevitability. Trump&amp;rsquo;s incompetence and repugnant presentation should have made this election an easy win for Democrats. It was anything but. The GOP will most likely retain control of the senate, and the Democratic majority in the house will shrink. In other words, the American voter has fired an incompetent narcissist but also emphatically rejected the agenda of his enemies. In this way, I think this election showed not only that American democracy is working but that it&amp;rsquo;s thriving. Now that the bull in the China shop is gone, the two parties have a chance to remake themselves and their policies for the future. Unfortunately, I think Democrats have already made up their minds in this regard. For the last four years, they have hallucinated a battle between the forces of good and evil, with themselves cast as a hero going up against a white supremacist tyrant. They have shown in the process that they understand neither racism, nor tyranny. I, for one, have no confidence that they will see the results of the election as anything other than victory. They will not learn a single lesson from the fact that after four years of screaming about Trump being racist and bigotted, he got more votes from women, minorities, immigrant and LGBTQ communities than any Republican in recent history. The crazy wing of progressives, the intersectionalists, the postmodernists, the identitarians, and the critical race theorists, may have an opportunity to run amok with the party. The Republicans, however, have an opportunity to cast themselves as the party of the working people of all backgrounds. This election has shown that the traditional notion of immigrants being by default Democrat voters is clearly untrue. I, for one, think immigrants tend to come to Western countries, and America in particular, for the same promises that America makes in its marketing. It is the land of opportunity and the place where you can succeed if you work hard, regardless of who you are. Progressives can scream all they want about inequality and try to recast American history with bigotry at its core. I think immigrants know better than anyone that this is nonsense, and Republicans have a chance to redraw the traditional lines of who their base is. I hope they take it. Much like 2016, this election has left people asking &amp;ldquo;how could 70M people still vote for Trump!?&amp;rdquo;. Let me offer two silver linings to the Trump administration that I&amp;rsquo;m not optimistic a Biden administration will get right: pushing back on the woke movement, and being hawkish on China. The single best thing Donald Trump has done in the last four years, as far as I&amp;rsquo;m concerned, is to sign an executive order banning critical race theory-based diversity and inclusion training in government and government contractors. Critical race theory is an inane and dangerous theory that puts people&amp;rsquo;s racial identity, as opposed to their individual character, at the core of their worth as people. Since the killing of George Floyd, critical theorists, like Robyn DeAngelo to name just one example, have been raking in big sums of cash delivering speeches and training seminars, where they tell their audience such nonsense as all white people are innately racist, or that white supremacy is at the core of western civilization. Outside of the novel coronavirus, this strain of thought is now the most dangerous virus sweeping across western society, and it&amp;rsquo;s one virus that the Trump administration has taken at least nominal action on. It&amp;rsquo;s doubtful that a Biden administration will get this right. On the other hand, traditional neoliberal politics and bipartisan support for globalization, precluded presidents before Trump from seeing US-China relations for what it really was: not as a way for the US to export democracy, but as a way for China to export its authoritarianism. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to imply that Trump&amp;rsquo;s hostile stance on China was principled or reasoned out in any way. That would be giving him too much credit. However, it had positive effects and was validated even more by the pandemic, where Americans realized exactly how dependent they were on a not-so-friendly foreign power. Pre-Trump politics put globalization and free trade as the top priority in relation with China, to the detriment of a long-term national security or geopolitical strategy. That free trade stance has not been reciprocated by China, and it has been exploited to export Chinese authorianism to the west. Many people don&amp;rsquo;t realize, for example, how easily Chinese censorship extends beyond Chinese borders. To name one trivial example, scripts for Holywood movies have to be pre-approved by the CCP if the studio has a chance of screening it in China. Effectively, that means none of us get to see a film that may draw the ire of Winnie the Poo Xi Jinping. I&amp;rsquo;m a free-market capitalist, but even I, in this case, see a need for government intervention. Will a Biden administration take on this task, or will it revert to the safety of well-known, but ineffective, policy? The truth is there really is a need to make America great again. Ironically, that need is a lot more severe today than it was four years ago, but to get here took a concerted effort. The pathologies of Donald Trump, American media, and the radical elements of the left wing all conspired to put American society in a four year psychosis. The traditional ways of America&amp;rsquo;s two parties are no longer adequate to meet the needs of its electorate at home or internationally. The gargantuan task facing the next president is to not just heal the patient but to set it up to thrive in a new world where continued American dominance is far from guaranteed and ideologies opposing core principles of liberal democracy are on the rise both domestically and internationally. Let&amp;rsquo;s wish him well.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Borat and Hurt Feelings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/10/25/borat-and-hurt-feelings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Borat and Hurt Feelings" /><published>2020-10-25T09:33:30-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-25T09:33:30-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/10/25/borat-and-hurt-feelings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/10/25/borat-and-hurt-feelings.html">&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting debate raging on Twitter, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nntaleb/status/1319976057693503490?s=20&quot;&gt;triggered by Nassim Taleb&lt;/a&gt;, about the racism in Borat. It seems pretty undeniable that Borat is deeply racist, and some of the techniques used in the movie to fool people into playing the butt of the joke is downright bullying. (See Zeynep Tufekci&amp;rsquo;s thread &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/zeynep/status/1320392228804694017?s=20&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, Borat also targets the approved-for-mocking segments of western society, so the people who are typically up in arms about endemic racism are not only silent but are cheering for it. It turns out, shitting on an ethnicity you can barely pronounce is a small price for catching Rudy Giuliani with his hand in his pants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a good measure of knowing where true power lies in society. If you think democracy is in danger because of right wing nuts or white supremacists, ask yourself who is more likely to pay a price for comedy: a comedian who mocks poor, low-education, white westerners and politicians who pander to them, or one that would similarly mocks, say, blacks or hispanics? Similarly, what kind of stereotyping would we accept as &amp;ldquo;just parody&amp;rdquo; and which ones would prompt widespread condemnation in newspapers of record?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for one, think Borat is racist, and that it&amp;rsquo;s OK. The answer to offensive speech is always more speech, not censoring it or calling for its cancellation or trying to outlaw it with piddling &amp;ldquo;hate speech&amp;rdquo; laws. Some speech will always cause someone&amp;rsquo;s feelings from being hurt. It&amp;rsquo;s fine. They&amp;rsquo;ll get over it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">There&amp;rsquo;s an interesting debate raging on Twitter, triggered by Nassim Taleb, about the racism in Borat. It seems pretty undeniable that Borat is deeply racist, and some of the techniques used in the movie to fool people into playing the butt of the joke is downright bullying. (See Zeynep Tufekci&amp;rsquo;s thread here) But, Borat also targets the approved-for-mocking segments of western society, so the people who are typically up in arms about endemic racism are not only silent but are cheering for it. It turns out, shitting on an ethnicity you can barely pronounce is a small price for catching Rudy Giuliani with his hand in his pants. This is a good measure of knowing where true power lies in society. If you think democracy is in danger because of right wing nuts or white supremacists, ask yourself who is more likely to pay a price for comedy: a comedian who mocks poor, low-education, white westerners and politicians who pander to them, or one that would similarly mocks, say, blacks or hispanics? Similarly, what kind of stereotyping would we accept as &amp;ldquo;just parody&amp;rdquo; and which ones would prompt widespread condemnation in newspapers of record? I, for one, think Borat is racist, and that it&amp;rsquo;s OK. The answer to offensive speech is always more speech, not censoring it or calling for its cancellation or trying to outlaw it with piddling &amp;ldquo;hate speech&amp;rdquo; laws. Some speech will always cause someone&amp;rsquo;s feelings from being hurt. It&amp;rsquo;s fine. They&amp;rsquo;ll get over it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning and Applying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/08/23/learning-and-applying.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning and Applying" /><published>2020-08-23T11:26:57-07:00</published><updated>2020-08-23T11:26:57-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/08/23/learning-and-applying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/08/23/learning-and-applying.html">&lt;p&gt;I remember the first time I set foot inside a large bookstore. I was about 13 years old, and something had broken with my computer, which I needed to play games. My teacher at the time suggested I read a book on how to fix computers myself. When I entered the computer books section of Chapters, my mind was blown by the sheer number of books. Something clicked in my head and I thought: &amp;ldquo;I need to read all of these!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that point on, I had an insatiable appetite for learning. The only exception to this were my university years – nothing can stifle a desire to learn like post-secondary education. I always imagined that given infinite resources and the ability to spend my time any way I wanted, I would just spend it learning and reading as much as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That notion is now deeply ingrained in my mind. But with age, I&amp;rsquo;m realizing how misguided it is. The bottleneck to learning is not just time to read. It is time to apply. True learning is impossible without meaningful application. We don&amp;rsquo;t learn through words but through all the senses. As the saying goes, &amp;ldquo;the rudder only works when the ship is moving&amp;rdquo; and building a large ship but never leaving port is simply a wasted investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always longed for the day when I can finally do nothing but learn. It&amp;rsquo;s easy for us to construct visions of an ideal future where we&amp;rsquo;ll be happier than now, and boundless time to read was (and is) a huge part of my utopian vision. But these visions are like dreams that don&amp;rsquo;t make sense upon a second inspection, and if we cling to them for too long or believe them too much, we&amp;rsquo;ll be unhappy when they (the impossible) are not realized. And if we do manage to achieve them, we&amp;rsquo;ll find that while all the conditions of our dreams are met, the envisioned happiness is not to be found, and we&amp;rsquo;ll repeat the cycle with a new vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this means that the range of topics and skills that I can truly learn and apply is much more limited than what I imagined in my head. It also means that I&amp;rsquo;m already living the life that I always wanted as much as is practical. If I was retired, the dials might get slightly tweaked and I may have a few extra hours per week to learn something or apply it. But life will not be radically different.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">I remember the first time I set foot inside a large bookstore. I was about 13 years old, and something had broken with my computer, which I needed to play games. My teacher at the time suggested I read a book on how to fix computers myself. When I entered the computer books section of Chapters, my mind was blown by the sheer number of books. Something clicked in my head and I thought: &amp;ldquo;I need to read all of these!&amp;rdquo; From that point on, I had an insatiable appetite for learning. The only exception to this were my university years – nothing can stifle a desire to learn like post-secondary education. I always imagined that given infinite resources and the ability to spend my time any way I wanted, I would just spend it learning and reading as much as I could. That notion is now deeply ingrained in my mind. But with age, I&amp;rsquo;m realizing how misguided it is. The bottleneck to learning is not just time to read. It is time to apply. True learning is impossible without meaningful application. We don&amp;rsquo;t learn through words but through all the senses. As the saying goes, &amp;ldquo;the rudder only works when the ship is moving&amp;rdquo; and building a large ship but never leaving port is simply a wasted investment. I&amp;rsquo;ve always longed for the day when I can finally do nothing but learn. It&amp;rsquo;s easy for us to construct visions of an ideal future where we&amp;rsquo;ll be happier than now, and boundless time to read was (and is) a huge part of my utopian vision. But these visions are like dreams that don&amp;rsquo;t make sense upon a second inspection, and if we cling to them for too long or believe them too much, we&amp;rsquo;ll be unhappy when they (the impossible) are not realized. And if we do manage to achieve them, we&amp;rsquo;ll find that while all the conditions of our dreams are met, the envisioned happiness is not to be found, and we&amp;rsquo;ll repeat the cycle with a new vision. All of this means that the range of topics and skills that I can truly learn and apply is much more limited than what I imagined in my head. It also means that I&amp;rsquo;m already living the life that I always wanted as much as is practical. If I was retired, the dials might get slightly tweaked and I may have a few extra hours per week to learn something or apply it. But life will not be radically different.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes From 7 Powers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/24/notes-from-7-powers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes From 7 Powers" /><published>2020-05-24T21:54:24-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-24T21:54:24-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/24/notes-from-7-powers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/24/notes-from-7-powers.html">&lt;p&gt;Why can some businesses generate vast amounts of profits while others can&amp;rsquo;t, even with comparable products and services? How can a manager ensure that his business can maintain healthy profit margins for extended periods of time without having those profits eroded by competition? How can an investor identify companies likely to generate healthy returns on capital?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these questions interest you, Hamilton Helmer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/7-Powers-Foundations-Business-Strategy/dp/0998116319&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; might be the most important book you&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of. Unlike most business books, its 210 pages are packed with valuable insight and clear explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a book on business strategy, and it addresses the topic at a foundational level. It aims to provide the reader with a &amp;ldquo;strategy compass&amp;rdquo;. For the manager of a business operation the strategy compass is a guide on navigating the trials of the business world to arrive (with some luck) at an attractive strategic position such that the business can command healthy profit margins and yet be protected from the arbitraging effect of competition. For the investor, the strategy compass provides a means of identifying strong and high-potential businesses that may not have been discovered yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff Bezos famously said &amp;ldquo;your margin is my opportunity&amp;rdquo;. This quote captures the dilemma for everyone who operates a business. A new venture starts by identifying a need for its customer base that has not been met. A solution is developed for this need and the business is off to a great start. Soon enough, however, others take notice and copycats emerge. They also want a piece of the pie, and what better way to compete with the pioneer than by undercutting their prices? Before long, the attractive profits enjoyed by the pioneering venture have been eroded by competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet some businesses are immune from this effect. In spite of years of developing competitive (or superior) technologies, AMD could never dethrone Intel as the dominant supplier of chips for PCs. What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between businesses that are immune to competition and those that are not? Helmer&amp;rsquo;s answer is that there are seven strategic positions (powers) that allow businesses to command high profits and keep them protected from competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are the seven powers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network effects&lt;/strong&gt;: Any product that improves as more people use it benefits from network effects. Facebook is the most uniquitous example of this. A social network is only as good as the friends you have on it. Facebook established itself as the dominant social network. This position was so powerful that in 2011, even $200B Google couldn&amp;rsquo;t challenge Facebook&amp;rsquo;s dominance with its Google+ offering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale economies&lt;/strong&gt;: Some products cost too much unless they&amp;rsquo;re made for a sufficiently large number of customers, such that the cost per each customer comes down. Microprocessors are a perfect example. They&amp;rsquo;re incredibly expensive to develop. Once Intel raced ahead in its market size, it became increasingly difficult for AMD to challenge them because Intel could outcompete AMD by spreading its costs across the larger customer base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switching costs&lt;/strong&gt;: Some products make it incredibly difficult for customers to switch once they have adopted the product. For example, a complicated piece of entreprise software requires expensive installation process. Then the workforce needs to be trained on the new software. Then the software needs to be supported on an ongoing basis. Each of these phases makes it less likely that the customer will consider an alternative vendor in the future. High installation costs are a deterrent. The need to re-train the workforce is another deterrent, and the personal relationships forged with the personnel of the existing vendor are yet another deterrent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Counter-positioning&lt;/strong&gt;: Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to challenge an incumbent by offering a unique angle on an existing product. The example Helmer provides is Vanguard. Its founder was thought insane by existing active money managers who charged large fees for their management services. Vanguard offered index funds with low fees and no active management. Even once the new approach proved popular and profitable, the incumbents had an institutional aversion to embracing it because it meant canibalizing their existing profitable businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Branding&lt;/strong&gt;: This one is pretty obvious. Brands are incredibly powerful and command loyalty from their base. However, they&amp;rsquo;re also one of the most elusive power types because they require persistent investment over a long period of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cornered resource&lt;/strong&gt;: A company can sustain high profit margins if it has exclusive control over a valuable resource. Here, &amp;ldquo;resource&amp;rdquo; can refer to anything from patents (as in the case of pharmaceuticals) to talent (as was the case of Pixar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;brain trust&amp;rdquo; consisting of Ed Catmull, John Lasseter, and Steve Jobs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process power&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the most rare of the powers. A company can develop a process that delivers superior results that cannot be copied by others. Helmer provides the example of the Toyota Production System. The company spent decades trying to optimize its manufacturing. When it became clear that Toyota was building superior cars, it even allowed staff from GM to observe its factories and question its staff. Still, GM could not reproduce Toyota&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are the seven powers. Companies that don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy at least one of these powers are bound to fall into a race-to-the-bottom as competitors erode their profit margins. For the interested reader, Helmer also shows mathematically the impact of each power type on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these powers include a benefit enjoyed by the winning business. Equally crucially, they create a barrier that makes it undesirable for others to compete with the winning business. This combination of benefit and barrier is what leads to power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmer calls these the &amp;ldquo;strategy statics&amp;rdquo;. These are desirable destinations for any business. How to reach these destinations is what Helmer calls &amp;ldquo;strategy dynamics&amp;rdquo;. These are my main takeaways on dynamics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategy is not made in a vaccum, it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/1987/07/crafting-strategy&quot;&gt;crafted&lt;/a&gt;. As Helmer puts it in the book, &amp;ldquo;the rudder only works when the ship is moving&amp;rdquo;. Nobody can invent a winning strategy in isolation. It requires the business leaders to be intimately familiar with every aspect of their business and their market. They need to keep their eyes on the seven destinations above and use their feel of their organizational capability and the market landscape to navigate to those destinations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The first cause of every Power is invention &amp;hellip; of product, process, business model, or brand.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The opportunity for invention arises out of external conditions. When these are ripe, the company uses its existing resources and capabilities to invent in any of the axes specified above to bring compelling value to market - value that is not currently offered by incumbents. Without the right combination of external conditions and invention, power can&amp;rsquo;t be achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An invention that brings compelling value to market, creates or significantly expands the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are three ways to bring compelling value to market:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capabilities-led. The company uses its capabilities to invent. The risk here is that there may not be a market for the invention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer-led. The company starts from the needs of the customers to invent. The risk here is that it may not have the right capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitor-led. Sometimes a competitor has successfully brought a compelling product to market but the company can invent a superior or adjacent product that expands the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Helmer points out that each of the seven powers need to be achieved in different phases of the company lifecycle. It does not make sense, for example, to invest heavily in the branding of a fledgling startup. Similarly, the time to achieve sufficient market share is during the early growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s a quick summary of Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass. I highly recommend you read the book if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in business strategy. I also recommend reading Henry Mintzberg&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/1987/07/crafting-strategy&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Crafting Strategy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; article that Helmer references. The notion that strategy is not designed but crafted rejects some approaches to strategy where managers who are distant from the business can get in a room and think their way to a strategy. It highlights the fact that ultimately, strategy comes down to judgement, which in turn comes down to an intimate familiarity with every facet of the organization, the customer base, and the industry. With this knowledge, good judgement, and a little luck, the manager can use Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass to navigate the business to one of the desirable destinations above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">Why can some businesses generate vast amounts of profits while others can&amp;rsquo;t, even with comparable products and services? How can a manager ensure that his business can maintain healthy profit margins for extended periods of time without having those profits eroded by competition? How can an investor identify companies likely to generate healthy returns on capital? If these questions interest you, Hamilton Helmer&amp;rsquo;s 7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy might be the most important book you&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of. Unlike most business books, its 210 pages are packed with valuable insight and clear explanations. This is a book on business strategy, and it addresses the topic at a foundational level. It aims to provide the reader with a &amp;ldquo;strategy compass&amp;rdquo;. For the manager of a business operation the strategy compass is a guide on navigating the trials of the business world to arrive (with some luck) at an attractive strategic position such that the business can command healthy profit margins and yet be protected from the arbitraging effect of competition. For the investor, the strategy compass provides a means of identifying strong and high-potential businesses that may not have been discovered yet. Jeff Bezos famously said &amp;ldquo;your margin is my opportunity&amp;rdquo;. This quote captures the dilemma for everyone who operates a business. A new venture starts by identifying a need for its customer base that has not been met. A solution is developed for this need and the business is off to a great start. Soon enough, however, others take notice and copycats emerge. They also want a piece of the pie, and what better way to compete with the pioneer than by undercutting their prices? Before long, the attractive profits enjoyed by the pioneering venture have been eroded by competitors. Yet some businesses are immune from this effect. In spite of years of developing competitive (or superior) technologies, AMD could never dethrone Intel as the dominant supplier of chips for PCs. What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between businesses that are immune to competition and those that are not? Helmer&amp;rsquo;s answer is that there are seven strategic positions (powers) that allow businesses to command high profits and keep them protected from competition. So what are the seven powers? Network effects: Any product that improves as more people use it benefits from network effects. Facebook is the most uniquitous example of this. A social network is only as good as the friends you have on it. Facebook established itself as the dominant social network. This position was so powerful that in 2011, even $200B Google couldn&amp;rsquo;t challenge Facebook&amp;rsquo;s dominance with its Google+ offering. Scale economies: Some products cost too much unless they&amp;rsquo;re made for a sufficiently large number of customers, such that the cost per each customer comes down. Microprocessors are a perfect example. They&amp;rsquo;re incredibly expensive to develop. Once Intel raced ahead in its market size, it became increasingly difficult for AMD to challenge them because Intel could outcompete AMD by spreading its costs across the larger customer base. Switching costs: Some products make it incredibly difficult for customers to switch once they have adopted the product. For example, a complicated piece of entreprise software requires expensive installation process. Then the workforce needs to be trained on the new software. Then the software needs to be supported on an ongoing basis. Each of these phases makes it less likely that the customer will consider an alternative vendor in the future. High installation costs are a deterrent. The need to re-train the workforce is another deterrent, and the personal relationships forged with the personnel of the existing vendor are yet another deterrent. Counter-positioning: Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to challenge an incumbent by offering a unique angle on an existing product. The example Helmer provides is Vanguard. Its founder was thought insane by existing active money managers who charged large fees for their management services. Vanguard offered index funds with low fees and no active management. Even once the new approach proved popular and profitable, the incumbents had an institutional aversion to embracing it because it meant canibalizing their existing profitable businesses. Branding: This one is pretty obvious. Brands are incredibly powerful and command loyalty from their base. However, they&amp;rsquo;re also one of the most elusive power types because they require persistent investment over a long period of time. Cornered resource: A company can sustain high profit margins if it has exclusive control over a valuable resource. Here, &amp;ldquo;resource&amp;rdquo; can refer to anything from patents (as in the case of pharmaceuticals) to talent (as was the case of Pixar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;brain trust&amp;rdquo; consisting of Ed Catmull, John Lasseter, and Steve Jobs). Process power: This is the most rare of the powers. A company can develop a process that delivers superior results that cannot be copied by others. Helmer provides the example of the Toyota Production System. The company spent decades trying to optimize its manufacturing. When it became clear that Toyota was building superior cars, it even allowed staff from GM to observe its factories and question its staff. Still, GM could not reproduce Toyota&amp;rsquo;s success. These are the seven powers. Companies that don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy at least one of these powers are bound to fall into a race-to-the-bottom as competitors erode their profit margins. For the interested reader, Helmer also shows mathematically the impact of each power type on the bottom line. Each of these powers include a benefit enjoyed by the winning business. Equally crucially, they create a barrier that makes it undesirable for others to compete with the winning business. This combination of benefit and barrier is what leads to power. Helmer calls these the &amp;ldquo;strategy statics&amp;rdquo;. These are desirable destinations for any business. How to reach these destinations is what Helmer calls &amp;ldquo;strategy dynamics&amp;rdquo;. These are my main takeaways on dynamics: Strategy is not made in a vaccum, it is crafted. As Helmer puts it in the book, &amp;ldquo;the rudder only works when the ship is moving&amp;rdquo;. Nobody can invent a winning strategy in isolation. It requires the business leaders to be intimately familiar with every aspect of their business and their market. They need to keep their eyes on the seven destinations above and use their feel of their organizational capability and the market landscape to navigate to those destinations. &amp;ldquo;The first cause of every Power is invention &amp;hellip; of product, process, business model, or brand.&amp;rdquo; The opportunity for invention arises out of external conditions. When these are ripe, the company uses its existing resources and capabilities to invent in any of the axes specified above to bring compelling value to market - value that is not currently offered by incumbents. Without the right combination of external conditions and invention, power can&amp;rsquo;t be achieved. An invention that brings compelling value to market, creates or significantly expands the market. There are three ways to bring compelling value to market: Capabilities-led. The company uses its capabilities to invent. The risk here is that there may not be a market for the invention. Customer-led. The company starts from the needs of the customers to invent. The risk here is that it may not have the right capabilities. Competitor-led. Sometimes a competitor has successfully brought a compelling product to market but the company can invent a superior or adjacent product that expands the market. Additionally, Helmer points out that each of the seven powers need to be achieved in different phases of the company lifecycle. It does not make sense, for example, to invest heavily in the branding of a fledgling startup. Similarly, the time to achieve sufficient market share is during the early growth. So that&amp;rsquo;s a quick summary of Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass. I highly recommend you read the book if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in business strategy. I also recommend reading Henry Mintzberg&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Crafting Strategy&amp;rdquo; article that Helmer references. The notion that strategy is not designed but crafted rejects some approaches to strategy where managers who are distant from the business can get in a room and think their way to a strategy. It highlights the fact that ultimately, strategy comes down to judgement, which in turn comes down to an intimate familiarity with every facet of the organization, the customer base, and the industry. With this knowledge, good judgement, and a little luck, the manager can use Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass to navigate the business to one of the desirable destinations above.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic Predictions (Part 3)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/17/pandemic-predictions-part-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic Predictions (Part 3)" /><published>2020-05-17T21:12:31-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-17T21:12:31-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/17/pandemic-predictions-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/17/pandemic-predictions-part-3.html">&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another (short) prediction about the long term effects of Coronavirus, along with a call for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s prediction relates to the airlines, and it&amp;rsquo;s closely related to the previous &lt;a href=&quot;http://hirad.ca/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2.html&quot;&gt;prediction around commercial real estate&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, I wanted to include this in that post, but I decided to dig for some data to paint a fuller picture. I failed on that front. If you&amp;rsquo;re good at business/industry analysis and you read this, I have a few asks for you at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the prediction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, I noted that I expect more and more workplaces to divest of their real estate and for remote work to become much more prevalent. Related to that, I foresee business travel to see a permanent reduction as a result of a much more widely-adopted remote work cultures. I can think of three types of business travel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that requires physical presence in a certain location. For example, a large engineering company may land a construction project far from their HQ and will need to send staff back and forth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that is more effective in-person. I think this is primarily sales. Building rapport with potential customers is much more effective in person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other. Companies often make people travel due to geographically-constrained workplaces, even though the nature of the work doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; being co-located.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I believe the last category, in the long run, will nearly vanish, as remote work becomes widely adopted and cost savings of less travel become possible and attractive. This will reduce demand for air travel from business customers. Demand will be further reduced in the second category as well - while some work is better done in person, the additional risk factor will move that cutoff line higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where having some data could&amp;rsquo;ve been useful. Given the above predictions, I would like to know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What portion of annual airline revenues come from business travellers and in which sectors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What portion of annual airline &lt;em&gt;profits&lt;/em&gt; come from business travellers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which airlines had the majority of their revenues and profits from business customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which routes do business travel revenues dominate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given the above information, one could make some further predictions about the airline industry in general. I &lt;em&gt;suspect&lt;/em&gt; that business travellers are less cost conscious than leisure travellers, and that business travellers are less likely to travel on discount airlines than on higher-end airlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a long timeline, I don&amp;rsquo;t think leisure travel will see much permanent reduction in demand. We&amp;rsquo;re not out of the woods yet with COVID19, and even cruise liners are seeing sales recover already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, without more data, these predictions can&amp;rsquo;t say much about how the supply side may change due to the predicted changes in demand. Here&amp;rsquo;s where my ask comes in: if you know where one can obtain the above stats, please get in touch and give me a hand - I&amp;rsquo;m flying blind here :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">Here&amp;rsquo;s another (short) prediction about the long term effects of Coronavirus, along with a call for help. Today&amp;rsquo;s prediction relates to the airlines, and it&amp;rsquo;s closely related to the previous prediction around commercial real estate. In fact, I wanted to include this in that post, but I decided to dig for some data to paint a fuller picture. I failed on that front. If you&amp;rsquo;re good at business/industry analysis and you read this, I have a few asks for you at the end. For the prediction: In the previous post, I noted that I expect more and more workplaces to divest of their real estate and for remote work to become much more prevalent. Related to that, I foresee business travel to see a permanent reduction as a result of a much more widely-adopted remote work cultures. I can think of three types of business travel: Work that requires physical presence in a certain location. For example, a large engineering company may land a construction project far from their HQ and will need to send staff back and forth. Work that is more effective in-person. I think this is primarily sales. Building rapport with potential customers is much more effective in person. Other. Companies often make people travel due to geographically-constrained workplaces, even though the nature of the work doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily require being co-located. I believe the last category, in the long run, will nearly vanish, as remote work becomes widely adopted and cost savings of less travel become possible and attractive. This will reduce demand for air travel from business customers. Demand will be further reduced in the second category as well - while some work is better done in person, the additional risk factor will move that cutoff line higher. Here&amp;rsquo;s where having some data could&amp;rsquo;ve been useful. Given the above predictions, I would like to know: What portion of annual airline revenues come from business travellers and in which sectors? What portion of annual airline profits come from business travellers? Which airlines had the majority of their revenues and profits from business customers? In which routes do business travel revenues dominate? Given the above information, one could make some further predictions about the airline industry in general. I suspect that business travellers are less cost conscious than leisure travellers, and that business travellers are less likely to travel on discount airlines than on higher-end airlines. On a long timeline, I don&amp;rsquo;t think leisure travel will see much permanent reduction in demand. We&amp;rsquo;re not out of the woods yet with COVID19, and even cruise liners are seeing sales recover already. Unfortunately, without more data, these predictions can&amp;rsquo;t say much about how the supply side may change due to the predicted changes in demand. Here&amp;rsquo;s where my ask comes in: if you know where one can obtain the above stats, please get in touch and give me a hand - I&amp;rsquo;m flying blind here :)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic Predictions (Part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic Predictions (Part 2)" /><published>2020-05-02T15:26:35-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-02T15:26:35-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2.html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hirad.ca/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about when we might go back to normal. Today, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what possible long-term ramifications the COVID19 pandemic might have. It would be an interesting thought exercise to do this for a variety of economic sectors. For this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll start with the most obvious long term impact: the impact on commercial real estate. This first became obvious to me about a week or two into North America being hit, and it has been pointed out by a number of writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a living post - I will update it as I think this through more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prediction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think commercial real estate is going to see a permanent drop in demand and therefore in prices. This does not hold true for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; types of commercial real estate, but it does hold true for many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Reasoning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An anecdote: my company recently got acquired by a bank. When we joined them, just a few months ago, people steeped in bank culture found the idea of remote work not only alien, but somewhat disturbing. On the other hand, walking 20-30 minutes between multiple towers in downtown Toronto for a meeting is something they don&amp;rsquo;t bat an eye at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, there is no legimate reason why business needs to be conducted that way - specially in technology-focused businesses. This was not a failure of capability, as much as it was a failure of culture. Coronavirus has shattered that culture. Everyone at those offices is now working from home. This is not to say that everyone &lt;em&gt;likes&lt;/em&gt; working from home right now (I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed having children is a particular impediment in enjoying WFH). But they&amp;rsquo;ve all been forced into a mandatory two-month-long trial, which is likely to continue. It&amp;rsquo;s a similar story across all sorts of businesses, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we&amp;rsquo;re through this pandemic, I expect everyone to return to business-as-usual. But I expect some key lessons will be learned from this about the benefits of remote work in cultures that would otherwise never imagine it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic is over, more workplaces will be offering remote work options for more types of roles. With this, lack of remote work options will become an impediment to hiring top talent, as it already has for tech hires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic is over, many workplaces will be reviewing how much they got done with everyone working from home, and they&amp;rsquo;ll be eyeing the expense line on their cash flows as a top candidate for cost-cutting. Even workplaces that are primarily office-based may need a reduced capacity as some portion of their workforce can work remotely at any given time. Large corporations that own their own real estate may see it as less essential and will be more likely to divest, increasing supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture shifts take time to be ingrained, but the pandemic has massively accelerated the shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of office space, many businesses will be innovating with a lower reliance on expensive, prime real estate. Cloud kitchens, for example, were a trend pre-pandemic, and that will only continue. If Amazon had habituated us to buy things online and get them a few days later, pandemic will take this to the next level, with delivery of all essentials becoming not just a preference, but a matter of safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big impediment to remote work is legal. When I bought my apartment, I had to commute for approx. 45 minutes to a lawyer&amp;rsquo;s office, sign a few documents in front of her (which took 5 minutes), then commute back for 45 minutes. This was and is infuriarting and nobody should accept it as &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;okay&amp;rsquo;. We have better ways, and the pandemic has also set the stage for updating our legal frameworks to be more remote-friendly – changes that would otherwise move at a glacial pace. For now, many of these changes are poised as temporary measures, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it&amp;rsquo;ll start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors will conspire to decrease the demand in commercial real estate. You&amp;rsquo;ve heard about the obvious winners in the current circumstance: remote communication tools, e-commerce, to name a few. This is the flipside of that coin - commercial real estate is the obvious loser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to be spending less time in wasteful commutes, and more time getting shit done. We&amp;rsquo;ll be happier, and in the very long term, we may even have more beautiful, less car-focused, more environmentally-friendly, and more decentralized cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The impact of this change on the urban landscape is another very interesting thread - to be pulled on in another post perhaps.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all types of commercial real estate will see this drop in demand, of course. As we spend more time in our homes, and more time away from a &amp;ldquo;downtown core&amp;rdquo;, we&amp;rsquo;ll need increasingly better infrastructure to serve our needs where we are. Many services that are currently concentrated in business districts will be downsized and spread more evenly across the urban landscape, closer to where people live.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">In the previous post, I talked about when we might go back to normal. Today, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what possible long-term ramifications the COVID19 pandemic might have. It would be an interesting thought exercise to do this for a variety of economic sectors. For this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll start with the most obvious long term impact: the impact on commercial real estate. This first became obvious to me about a week or two into North America being hit, and it has been pointed out by a number of writers. This is a living post - I will update it as I think this through more deeply. Prediction I think commercial real estate is going to see a permanent drop in demand and therefore in prices. This does not hold true for all types of commercial real estate, but it does hold true for many. My Reasoning An anecdote: my company recently got acquired by a bank. When we joined them, just a few months ago, people steeped in bank culture found the idea of remote work not only alien, but somewhat disturbing. On the other hand, walking 20-30 minutes between multiple towers in downtown Toronto for a meeting is something they don&amp;rsquo;t bat an eye at. In 2020, there is no legimate reason why business needs to be conducted that way - specially in technology-focused businesses. This was not a failure of capability, as much as it was a failure of culture. Coronavirus has shattered that culture. Everyone at those offices is now working from home. This is not to say that everyone likes working from home right now (I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed having children is a particular impediment in enjoying WFH). But they&amp;rsquo;ve all been forced into a mandatory two-month-long trial, which is likely to continue. It&amp;rsquo;s a similar story across all sorts of businesses, of course. Once we&amp;rsquo;re through this pandemic, I expect everyone to return to business-as-usual. But I expect some key lessons will be learned from this about the benefits of remote work in cultures that would otherwise never imagine it. When the pandemic is over, more workplaces will be offering remote work options for more types of roles. With this, lack of remote work options will become an impediment to hiring top talent, as it already has for tech hires. When the pandemic is over, many workplaces will be reviewing how much they got done with everyone working from home, and they&amp;rsquo;ll be eyeing the expense line on their cash flows as a top candidate for cost-cutting. Even workplaces that are primarily office-based may need a reduced capacity as some portion of their workforce can work remotely at any given time. Large corporations that own their own real estate may see it as less essential and will be more likely to divest, increasing supply. Culture shifts take time to be ingrained, but the pandemic has massively accelerated the shift. Outside of office space, many businesses will be innovating with a lower reliance on expensive, prime real estate. Cloud kitchens, for example, were a trend pre-pandemic, and that will only continue. If Amazon had habituated us to buy things online and get them a few days later, pandemic will take this to the next level, with delivery of all essentials becoming not just a preference, but a matter of safety. One big impediment to remote work is legal. When I bought my apartment, I had to commute for approx. 45 minutes to a lawyer&amp;rsquo;s office, sign a few documents in front of her (which took 5 minutes), then commute back for 45 minutes. This was and is infuriarting and nobody should accept it as &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;okay&amp;rsquo;. We have better ways, and the pandemic has also set the stage for updating our legal frameworks to be more remote-friendly – changes that would otherwise move at a glacial pace. For now, many of these changes are poised as temporary measures, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it&amp;rsquo;ll start. All of these factors will conspire to decrease the demand in commercial real estate. You&amp;rsquo;ve heard about the obvious winners in the current circumstance: remote communication tools, e-commerce, to name a few. This is the flipside of that coin - commercial real estate is the obvious loser. We&amp;rsquo;re going to be spending less time in wasteful commutes, and more time getting shit done. We&amp;rsquo;ll be happier, and in the very long term, we may even have more beautiful, less car-focused, more environmentally-friendly, and more decentralized cities. (The impact of this change on the urban landscape is another very interesting thread - to be pulled on in another post perhaps.) Not all types of commercial real estate will see this drop in demand, of course. As we spend more time in our homes, and more time away from a &amp;ldquo;downtown core&amp;rdquo;, we&amp;rsquo;ll need increasingly better infrastructure to serve our needs where we are. Many services that are currently concentrated in business districts will be downsized and spread more evenly across the urban landscape, closer to where people live.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic Predictions (Part 1)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic Predictions (Part 1)" /><published>2020-04-26T18:19:30-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T18:19:30-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1.html">&lt;p&gt;Like everyone else, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a number of conversation in the last few weeks around the question of &amp;ldquo;when will we go back to normal?&amp;rdquo;. So here&amp;rsquo;s how I think we need to approach the answer, based on my readings so far. The TL;DR is &amp;ldquo;not soon&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to understand why this virus is problematic. It&amp;rsquo;s not just that the disease is so bad. Even though it is bad, we can treat most people who get it. The main issue is that it&amp;rsquo;s spreading so fast, and that means overwhelming the healthcare system. Medicine may &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo; how to help someone, but if there are no doctors or hospital beds or other equipment to deliver the treatment, the knowledge does us no good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the main risk is overloading the health care system. Therefore, &amp;ldquo;when will we go back to normal&amp;rdquo; is really asking &amp;ldquo;when can we do everything we used to do, without running the risk of overloading the health care system?&amp;rdquo;. That question in turn is really asking &amp;ldquo;when will we be confident there won&amp;rsquo;t be a surge of infections from our day-to-day activities?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be confident of that there won&amp;rsquo;t be a surge, one of the following must be true:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a vaccine. This is, in the best case, 1.5-2 years out. Additionally, once a vaccine exists, it must be manufactured in sufficiently large quantities. Likely, it&amp;rsquo;ll have gradual rollout, and that will take time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have herd immunity. This is also either very slow (order of years) or very catastrophic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a treatment. A vaccine is not strictly neccessary, if we can find treatments that won&amp;rsquo;t require prolonged, intense hospitalizations for the most-affected patients. I haven&amp;rsquo;t read anything about this, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how likely it is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have pervasive and fast testing. Having this requires competent planning and execution. We seem to be in a pretty good place on that front in Canada and specially in BC. However, this path also requires access to equipment/manufacturing capacity, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if we can get that in Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From what I can tell, barring some miraculous breakthrough, achieving any of these solutions at a sufficiently large scale is an effort in the order of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming we have one of these options available, we must subtract from this asset any liability that will put its gains at risk. For example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will individuals who have had the virus be able to get sick from it again? (The fact that we don&amp;rsquo;t know this six months later should give a sense of the timeline before we can get a handle on it.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the Canadian government buckle under some political pressure &amp;amp; open the border with the USA? If that happens, we can have American pee in our pool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will we allow foreign travel/tourism? Again, if we&amp;rsquo;re doing well locally, but we don&amp;rsquo;t have closed borders, we can be inviting the virus from abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; we come up with be optional or mandatory? If we find a vaccine tomorrow, how many hicks will refuse to vaccinate to avoid autism, for example? If we do pervasive testing, can some people opt-out and yet go about their day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say, I doubt we&amp;rsquo;re going back to normal any time soon, not for years - until we have a vaccine and/or herd immunity. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we&amp;rsquo;ll be in lockdown or staying home the whole time. I think the most likely scenario – the option that seems most immediately available – is that we will cycle through periods of lockdown and relaxing restrictions. We won&amp;rsquo;t really flatten the curve, we&amp;rsquo;ll break it down into several smaller curves over a longer time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things, like international travel or large-crowd events (concerts, sports), will be the last to make a come back. Other activities can come back more quickly. We may be able to hang out in small groups. Some public spaces may be able to open with some restrictions (like mandatory masks). Some workplaces may be able to operate in-person again (should they still want to). And I sure hope BC will open its provincial parks again. But we should not hope to go back to living the way we used to any time soon. In fact, we probably never will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long period of living under restrictions will re-shape society. We will find new ways of doing the things we did before, and we may find that the new ways are, in some cases, not so bad. For example, more people will work from home permanently. This will have widespread ramifications for the economy. I &lt;em&gt;hope&lt;/em&gt; to follow up with additional posts on how I think this situation will affect different industries. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Like everyone else, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a number of conversation in the last few weeks around the question of &amp;ldquo;when will we go back to normal?&amp;rdquo;. So here&amp;rsquo;s how I think we need to approach the answer, based on my readings so far. The TL;DR is &amp;ldquo;not soon&amp;rdquo;.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Trust the Peacock</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/11/12/dont-trust-the-peacock.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don't Trust the Peacock" /><published>2018-11-12T17:44:58-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-12T17:44:58-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/11/12/dont-trust-the-peacock</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/11/12/dont-trust-the-peacock.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the great Tao is forgotten,
goodness and piety appear.
When the body&amp;rsquo;s intelligence declines,
cleverness and knowledge step forth.
When there is no peace in the family,
filial piety begins.
When the country falls into chaos,
patriotism is born.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- &lt;strong&gt;Lao Tzu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say judging people is bad. I’m not sure I agree. Regardless, we all do it anyway. I want to continuously improve my heuristics to make good judgements of people. Good heuristics are rare, but I have one that’s fairly reliable that I’m going to share with you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last year, I attended a ten day meditation retreat. There was one specific individual at this retreat who stood out. He was an “old student”, which means he had done at least one ten-day course before. While the attendees were socializing at the meditation centre before the beginning of the course and before Noble Silence was to be observed, he was sitting quietly in a corner. If someone tried to speak to him, he would turn his head toward them extremely slowly, give the shortest possible answer, and go back to being quiet. In addition to his behaviour, he also stood out because of his appearance. He was wearing what looked like rags — what you might expect to see on a beggar on an Indian street. Except it didn’t look authentic. The rags were quite nice. It was what you might expect to see from a well-off white guy impersonating a poor Indian beggar. He also walked barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time I noticed him was on the last day of the retreat. For ten days, we had all been silent. On the last day, Noble Silence ended and people started chattering again. However, talking was still disallowed in the main meditation hall. At one point, while some people were talking in the hallway, I was in the meditation hall, trying to practice. This individual was also there, sitting a few rows in front of me. In between us, two people started talking. The meditation hall was already not so quiet, considering that the chatter from the hallway was easily audible. The additional noise from the two talkers inside the hall was too much for this individual to bear. He turned around and gave the two talkers an angry “SSSSHHHHH!!!”. I’ll never forget the look of rage on his face. Ten days of working on increasing compassion had evaporated in an instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This individual, in my mind, represents the quintessential “peacock” in a community. He went to great lengths to put on appearances about his devotion to the practice, but at the end of the day, he exhibited none of the skill. Peacocks exist in every walk of life, and observing many of them has led me to this heuristic: I am instantly suspicious of people who are putting on excessive appearances. These appearances can be visual (eg. clothing) or behavioural (eg. acting overly sensitive to certain subjects) or verbal (eg. the proverbial “blowing of one’s own trumpet”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this peacocking is to elevate one’s status in a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peacocks thrive in environments where the authenticity of status signals are hard to gauge. In the tech community, peacocking is difficult. You can’t fool people into thinking you’re a good engineer by putting on thicker glasses and lowering your social skills. At the end of the day, you’ll have to speak knowledgeably and write good code. Nassim Taleb has pointed out in &lt;em&gt;Skin In The Game&lt;/em&gt;, the ultimate authentic signal is courage: a display of courage &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; proof of its true existence. Most signals that people send each other don’t have this high of a signal-to-substance ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, zouk and aikido communities that I’m part of are rife with peacocks. In zouk, these people gravitate toward a style of dance that (they think) does not require rigorous work on fundamentals. They might state that feeling is more important than technique. They might wear genie pants to look like time-travelling hippies who escaped their commune in the ’60s. The teachers they idolize look this way, so they copy the appearance. Those teachers, however, are often highly skilled, but where their technique might take years of hard practice to copy, their outward appearance can be copied very quickly and used as a status signal in the community. These people often don’t have a regular teacher that they train under, but they attend all the big events and sometimes take private lessons, which they use as an opportunity to &amp;ldquo;socialize&amp;rdquo; with well-known teachers and tell their friends about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In aikido, the story is not so different. Strength and stamina are often used to signal skill in aikido where there is none. Unnecessarily long or elaborate demonstrations are used to impress untrained spectators or equally unskilled peers. The trained eye can see that every technique in these demonstrations is performed with the most egregious mistakes. Often, similar to the zouk peacocks, the aikido peacocks will attend seminars with famous teachers with no attention whatever to the lessons being taught. They love collecting a large catalogue of famous teachers who they can claim they’ve trained under. They might collect photos with these teachers, in which they’ll pose like thugs with a stern face and clenched fists to make sure they look tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to emphasize that merely sending these signals by itself is not evidence of anything wrong. Strength and stamina are not bad things. Attending lots of seminars is not a bad thing. Looking like a hippie&amp;hellip; well, ok, that one’s unforgivable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue with peacocks is not just that they send these signals. It’s that they’re signalling a lie. They want you to believe they possess substance that they simply don’t. Substance is hard to gauge, but we notice others’ signals right away. But here’s the thing about people with substance: they are in no rush and they can wait for you to see theirs. They’re confident and reassured. Peacocks are neither of these things. So when I see someone sending signals a little too loudly, I think the lady doth protest too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heuristics are not perfect, and I try to give people a chance even when my peacock radar is going off. But I’ve often been right about peacocks, and whatever any individual’s merits may be, peacocking is at the very least a sign of disingenuity and perhaps dishonesty. In communities where they can thrive, peacocks will eventually become teachers or leaders, and they will mislead entire contingents of beginners who don’t know any better about choosing who to follow. That is the biggest harm of the peacock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When the great Tao is forgotten, goodness and piety appear. When the body&amp;rsquo;s intelligence declines, cleverness and knowledge step forth. When there is no peace in the family, filial piety begins. When the country falls into chaos, patriotism is born. - Lao Tzu They say judging people is bad. I’m not sure I agree. Regardless, we all do it anyway. I want to continuously improve my heuristics to make good judgements of people. Good heuristics are rare, but I have one that’s fairly reliable that I’m going to share with you here. Last year, I attended a ten day meditation retreat. There was one specific individual at this retreat who stood out. He was an “old student”, which means he had done at least one ten-day course before. While the attendees were socializing at the meditation centre before the beginning of the course and before Noble Silence was to be observed, he was sitting quietly in a corner. If someone tried to speak to him, he would turn his head toward them extremely slowly, give the shortest possible answer, and go back to being quiet. In addition to his behaviour, he also stood out because of his appearance. He was wearing what looked like rags — what you might expect to see on a beggar on an Indian street. Except it didn’t look authentic. The rags were quite nice. It was what you might expect to see from a well-off white guy impersonating a poor Indian beggar. He also walked barefoot. The next time I noticed him was on the last day of the retreat. For ten days, we had all been silent. On the last day, Noble Silence ended and people started chattering again. However, talking was still disallowed in the main meditation hall. At one point, while some people were talking in the hallway, I was in the meditation hall, trying to practice. This individual was also there, sitting a few rows in front of me. In between us, two people started talking. The meditation hall was already not so quiet, considering that the chatter from the hallway was easily audible. The additional noise from the two talkers inside the hall was too much for this individual to bear. He turned around and gave the two talkers an angry “SSSSHHHHH!!!”. I’ll never forget the look of rage on his face. Ten days of working on increasing compassion had evaporated in an instance. This individual, in my mind, represents the quintessential “peacock” in a community. He went to great lengths to put on appearances about his devotion to the practice, but at the end of the day, he exhibited none of the skill. Peacocks exist in every walk of life, and observing many of them has led me to this heuristic: I am instantly suspicious of people who are putting on excessive appearances. These appearances can be visual (eg. clothing) or behavioural (eg. acting overly sensitive to certain subjects) or verbal (eg. the proverbial “blowing of one’s own trumpet”). The purpose of this peacocking is to elevate one’s status in a community. Peacocks thrive in environments where the authenticity of status signals are hard to gauge. In the tech community, peacocking is difficult. You can’t fool people into thinking you’re a good engineer by putting on thicker glasses and lowering your social skills. At the end of the day, you’ll have to speak knowledgeably and write good code. Nassim Taleb has pointed out in Skin In The Game, the ultimate authentic signal is courage: a display of courage is proof of its true existence. Most signals that people send each other don’t have this high of a signal-to-substance ratio. For example, zouk and aikido communities that I’m part of are rife with peacocks. In zouk, these people gravitate toward a style of dance that (they think) does not require rigorous work on fundamentals. They might state that feeling is more important than technique. They might wear genie pants to look like time-travelling hippies who escaped their commune in the ’60s. The teachers they idolize look this way, so they copy the appearance. Those teachers, however, are often highly skilled, but where their technique might take years of hard practice to copy, their outward appearance can be copied very quickly and used as a status signal in the community. These people often don’t have a regular teacher that they train under, but they attend all the big events and sometimes take private lessons, which they use as an opportunity to &amp;ldquo;socialize&amp;rdquo; with well-known teachers and tell their friends about it. In aikido, the story is not so different. Strength and stamina are often used to signal skill in aikido where there is none. Unnecessarily long or elaborate demonstrations are used to impress untrained spectators or equally unskilled peers. The trained eye can see that every technique in these demonstrations is performed with the most egregious mistakes. Often, similar to the zouk peacocks, the aikido peacocks will attend seminars with famous teachers with no attention whatever to the lessons being taught. They love collecting a large catalogue of famous teachers who they can claim they’ve trained under. They might collect photos with these teachers, in which they’ll pose like thugs with a stern face and clenched fists to make sure they look tough. It’s important to emphasize that merely sending these signals by itself is not evidence of anything wrong. Strength and stamina are not bad things. Attending lots of seminars is not a bad thing. Looking like a hippie&amp;hellip; well, ok, that one’s unforgivable. The issue with peacocks is not just that they send these signals. It’s that they’re signalling a lie. They want you to believe they possess substance that they simply don’t. Substance is hard to gauge, but we notice others’ signals right away. But here’s the thing about people with substance: they are in no rush and they can wait for you to see theirs. They’re confident and reassured. Peacocks are neither of these things. So when I see someone sending signals a little too loudly, I think the lady doth protest too much. Heuristics are not perfect, and I try to give people a chance even when my peacock radar is going off. But I’ve often been right about peacocks, and whatever any individual’s merits may be, peacocking is at the very least a sign of disingenuity and perhaps dishonesty. In communities where they can thrive, peacocks will eventually become teachers or leaders, and they will mislead entire contingents of beginners who don’t know any better about choosing who to follow. That is the biggest harm of the peacock.</summary></entry></feed>