<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-20T22:33:19-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Making the map match the territory</title><entry><title type="html">Notes From 7 Powers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/24/notes-from-7-powers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes From 7 Powers" /><published>2020-05-24T21:54:24-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-24T21:54:24-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/24/notes-from-7-powers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/24/notes-from-7-powers.html">&lt;p&gt;Why can some businesses generate vast amounts of profits while others can&amp;rsquo;t, even with comparable products and services? How can a manager ensure that his business can maintain healthy profit margins for extended periods of time without having those profits eroded by competition? How can an investor identify companies likely to generate healthy returns on capital?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these questions interest you, Hamilton Helmer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/7-Powers-Foundations-Business-Strategy/dp/0998116319&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; might be the most important book you&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of. Unlike most business books, its 210 pages are packed with valuable insight and clear explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a book on business strategy, and it addresses the topic at a foundational level. It aims to provide the reader with a &amp;ldquo;strategy compass&amp;rdquo;. For the manager of a business operation the strategy compass is a guide on navigating the trials of the business world to arrive (with some luck) at an attractive strategic position such that the business can command healthy profit margins and yet be protected from the arbitraging effect of competition. For the investor, the strategy compass provides a means of identifying strong and high-potential businesses that may not have been discovered yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff Bezos famously said &amp;ldquo;your margin is my opportunity&amp;rdquo;. This quote captures the dilemma for everyone who operates a business. A new venture starts by identifying a need for its customer base that has not been met. A solution is developed for this need and the business is off to a great start. Soon enough, however, others take notice and copycats emerge. They also want a piece of the pie, and what better way to compete with the pioneer than by undercutting their prices? Before long, the attractive profits enjoyed by the pioneering venture have been eroded by competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet some businesses are immune from this effect. In spite of years of developing competitive (or superior) technologies, AMD could never dethrone Intel as the dominant supplier of chips for PCs. What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between businesses that are immune to competition and those that are not? Helmer&amp;rsquo;s answer is that there are seven strategic positions (powers) that allow businesses to command high profits and keep them protected from competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are the seven powers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network effects&lt;/strong&gt;: Any product that improves as more people use it benefits from network effects. Facebook is the most uniquitous example of this. A social network is only as good as the friends you have on it. Facebook established itself as the dominant social network. This position was so powerful that in 2011, even $200B Google couldn&amp;rsquo;t challenge Facebook&amp;rsquo;s dominance with its Google+ offering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scale economies&lt;/strong&gt;: Some products cost too much unless they&amp;rsquo;re made for a sufficiently large number of customers, such that the cost per each customer comes down. Microprocessors are a perfect example. They&amp;rsquo;re incredibly expensive to develop. Once Intel raced ahead in its market size, it became increasingly difficult for AMD to challenge them because Intel could outcompete AMD by spreading its costs across the larger customer base.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switching costs&lt;/strong&gt;: Some products make it incredibly difficult for customers to switch once they have adopted the product. For example, a complicated piece of entreprise software requires expensive installation process. Then the workforce needs to be trained on the new software. Then the software needs to be supported on an ongoing basis. Each of these phases makes it less likely that the customer will consider an alternative vendor in the future. High installation costs are a deterrent. The need to re-train the workforce is another deterrent, and the personal relationships forged with the personnel of the existing vendor are yet another deterrent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Counter-positioning&lt;/strong&gt;: Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to challenge an incumbent by offering a unique angle on an existing product. The example Helmer provides is Vanguard. Its founder was thought insane by existing active money managers who charged large fees for their management services. Vanguard offered index funds with low fees and no active management. Even once the new approach proved popular and profitable, the incumbents had an institutional aversion to embracing it because it meant canibalizing their existing profitable businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Branding&lt;/strong&gt;: This one is pretty obvious. Brands are incredibly powerful and command loyalty from their base. However, they&amp;rsquo;re also one of the most elusive power types because they require persistent investment over a long period of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cornered resource&lt;/strong&gt;: A company can sustain high profit margins if it has exclusive control over a valuable resource. Here, &amp;ldquo;resource&amp;rdquo; can refer to anything from patents (as in the case of pharmaceuticals) to talent (as was the case of Pixar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;brain trust&amp;rdquo; consisting of Ed Catmull, John Lasseter, and Steve Jobs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process power&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the most rare of the powers. A company can develop a process that delivers superior results that cannot be copied by others. Helmer provides the example of the Toyota Production System. The company spent decades trying to optimize its manufacturing. When it became clear that Toyota was building superior cars, it even allowed staff from GM to observe its factories and question its staff. Still, GM could not reproduce Toyota&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These are the seven powers. Companies that don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy at least one of these powers are bound to fall into a race-to-the-bottom as competitors erode their profit margins. For the interested reader, Helmer also shows mathematically the impact of each power type on the bottom line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these powers include a benefit enjoyed by the winning business. Equally crucially, they create a barrier that makes it undesirable for others to compete with the winning business. This combination of benefit and barrier is what leads to power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmer calls these the &amp;ldquo;strategy statics&amp;rdquo;. These are desirable destinations for any business. How to reach these destinations is what Helmer calls &amp;ldquo;strategy dynamics&amp;rdquo;. These are my main takeaways on dynamics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategy is not made in a vaccum, it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/1987/07/crafting-strategy&quot;&gt;crafted&lt;/a&gt;. As Helmer puts it in the book, &amp;ldquo;the rudder only works when the ship is moving&amp;rdquo;. Nobody can invent a winning strategy in isolation. It requires the business leaders to be intimately familiar with every aspect of their business and their market. They need to keep their eyes on the seven destinations above and use their feel of their organizational capability and the market landscape to navigate to those destinations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The first cause of every Power is invention &amp;hellip; of product, process, business model, or brand.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The opportunity for invention arises out of external conditions. When these are ripe, the company uses its existing resources and capabilities to invent in any of the axes specified above to bring compelling value to market - value that is not currently offered by incumbents. Without the right combination of external conditions and invention, power can&amp;rsquo;t be achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An invention that brings compelling value to market, creates or significantly expands the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are three ways to bring compelling value to market:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capabilities-led. The company uses its capabilities to invent. The risk here is that there may not be a market for the invention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer-led. The company starts from the needs of the customers to invent. The risk here is that it may not have the right capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitor-led. Sometimes a competitor has successfully brought a compelling product to market but the company can invent a superior or adjacent product that expands the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Helmer points out that each of the seven powers need to be achieved in different phases of the company lifecycle. It does not make sense, for example, to invest heavily in the branding of a fledgling startup. Similarly, the time to achieve sufficient market share is during the early growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s a quick summary of Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass. I highly recommend you read the book if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in business strategy. I also recommend reading Henry Mintzberg&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/1987/07/crafting-strategy&quot;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Crafting Strategy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; article that Helmer references. The notion that strategy is not designed but crafted rejects some approaches to strategy where managers who are distant from the business can get in a room and think their way to a strategy. It highlights the fact that ultimately, strategy comes down to judgement, which in turn comes down to an intimate familiarity with every facet of the organization, the customer base, and the industry. With this knowledge, good judgement, and a little luck, the manager can use Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass to navigate the business to one of the desirable destinations above.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">Why can some businesses generate vast amounts of profits while others can&amp;rsquo;t, even with comparable products and services? How can a manager ensure that his business can maintain healthy profit margins for extended periods of time without having those profits eroded by competition? How can an investor identify companies likely to generate healthy returns on capital? If these questions interest you, Hamilton Helmer&amp;rsquo;s 7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy might be the most important book you&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of. Unlike most business books, its 210 pages are packed with valuable insight and clear explanations. This is a book on business strategy, and it addresses the topic at a foundational level. It aims to provide the reader with a &amp;ldquo;strategy compass&amp;rdquo;. For the manager of a business operation the strategy compass is a guide on navigating the trials of the business world to arrive (with some luck) at an attractive strategic position such that the business can command healthy profit margins and yet be protected from the arbitraging effect of competition. For the investor, the strategy compass provides a means of identifying strong and high-potential businesses that may not have been discovered yet. Jeff Bezos famously said &amp;ldquo;your margin is my opportunity&amp;rdquo;. This quote captures the dilemma for everyone who operates a business. A new venture starts by identifying a need for its customer base that has not been met. A solution is developed for this need and the business is off to a great start. Soon enough, however, others take notice and copycats emerge. They also want a piece of the pie, and what better way to compete with the pioneer than by undercutting their prices? Before long, the attractive profits enjoyed by the pioneering venture have been eroded by competitors. Yet some businesses are immune from this effect. In spite of years of developing competitive (or superior) technologies, AMD could never dethrone Intel as the dominant supplier of chips for PCs. What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between businesses that are immune to competition and those that are not? Helmer&amp;rsquo;s answer is that there are seven strategic positions (powers) that allow businesses to command high profits and keep them protected from competition. So what are the seven powers? Network effects: Any product that improves as more people use it benefits from network effects. Facebook is the most uniquitous example of this. A social network is only as good as the friends you have on it. Facebook established itself as the dominant social network. This position was so powerful that in 2011, even $200B Google couldn&amp;rsquo;t challenge Facebook&amp;rsquo;s dominance with its Google+ offering. Scale economies: Some products cost too much unless they&amp;rsquo;re made for a sufficiently large number of customers, such that the cost per each customer comes down. Microprocessors are a perfect example. They&amp;rsquo;re incredibly expensive to develop. Once Intel raced ahead in its market size, it became increasingly difficult for AMD to challenge them because Intel could outcompete AMD by spreading its costs across the larger customer base. Switching costs: Some products make it incredibly difficult for customers to switch once they have adopted the product. For example, a complicated piece of entreprise software requires expensive installation process. Then the workforce needs to be trained on the new software. Then the software needs to be supported on an ongoing basis. Each of these phases makes it less likely that the customer will consider an alternative vendor in the future. High installation costs are a deterrent. The need to re-train the workforce is another deterrent, and the personal relationships forged with the personnel of the existing vendor are yet another deterrent. Counter-positioning: Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to challenge an incumbent by offering a unique angle on an existing product. The example Helmer provides is Vanguard. Its founder was thought insane by existing active money managers who charged large fees for their management services. Vanguard offered index funds with low fees and no active management. Even once the new approach proved popular and profitable, the incumbents had an institutional aversion to embracing it because it meant canibalizing their existing profitable businesses. Branding: This one is pretty obvious. Brands are incredibly powerful and command loyalty from their base. However, they&amp;rsquo;re also one of the most elusive power types because they require persistent investment over a long period of time. Cornered resource: A company can sustain high profit margins if it has exclusive control over a valuable resource. Here, &amp;ldquo;resource&amp;rdquo; can refer to anything from patents (as in the case of pharmaceuticals) to talent (as was the case of Pixar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;brain trust&amp;rdquo; consisting of Ed Catmull, John Lasseter, and Steve Jobs). Process power: This is the most rare of the powers. A company can develop a process that delivers superior results that cannot be copied by others. Helmer provides the example of the Toyota Production System. The company spent decades trying to optimize its manufacturing. When it became clear that Toyota was building superior cars, it even allowed staff from GM to observe its factories and question its staff. Still, GM could not reproduce Toyota&amp;rsquo;s success. These are the seven powers. Companies that don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy at least one of these powers are bound to fall into a race-to-the-bottom as competitors erode their profit margins. For the interested reader, Helmer also shows mathematically the impact of each power type on the bottom line. Each of these powers include a benefit enjoyed by the winning business. Equally crucially, they create a barrier that makes it undesirable for others to compete with the winning business. This combination of benefit and barrier is what leads to power. Helmer calls these the &amp;ldquo;strategy statics&amp;rdquo;. These are desirable destinations for any business. How to reach these destinations is what Helmer calls &amp;ldquo;strategy dynamics&amp;rdquo;. These are my main takeaways on dynamics: Strategy is not made in a vaccum, it is crafted. As Helmer puts it in the book, &amp;ldquo;the rudder only works when the ship is moving&amp;rdquo;. Nobody can invent a winning strategy in isolation. It requires the business leaders to be intimately familiar with every aspect of their business and their market. They need to keep their eyes on the seven destinations above and use their feel of their organizational capability and the market landscape to navigate to those destinations. &amp;ldquo;The first cause of every Power is invention &amp;hellip; of product, process, business model, or brand.&amp;rdquo; The opportunity for invention arises out of external conditions. When these are ripe, the company uses its existing resources and capabilities to invent in any of the axes specified above to bring compelling value to market - value that is not currently offered by incumbents. Without the right combination of external conditions and invention, power can&amp;rsquo;t be achieved. An invention that brings compelling value to market, creates or significantly expands the market. There are three ways to bring compelling value to market: Capabilities-led. The company uses its capabilities to invent. The risk here is that there may not be a market for the invention. Customer-led. The company starts from the needs of the customers to invent. The risk here is that it may not have the right capabilities. Competitor-led. Sometimes a competitor has successfully brought a compelling product to market but the company can invent a superior or adjacent product that expands the market. Additionally, Helmer points out that each of the seven powers need to be achieved in different phases of the company lifecycle. It does not make sense, for example, to invest heavily in the branding of a fledgling startup. Similarly, the time to achieve sufficient market share is during the early growth. So that&amp;rsquo;s a quick summary of Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass. I highly recommend you read the book if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in business strategy. I also recommend reading Henry Mintzberg&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Crafting Strategy&amp;rdquo; article that Helmer references. The notion that strategy is not designed but crafted rejects some approaches to strategy where managers who are distant from the business can get in a room and think their way to a strategy. It highlights the fact that ultimately, strategy comes down to judgement, which in turn comes down to an intimate familiarity with every facet of the organization, the customer base, and the industry. With this knowledge, good judgement, and a little luck, the manager can use Helmer&amp;rsquo;s strategy compass to navigate the business to one of the desirable destinations above.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic Predictions (Part 3)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/17/pandemic-predictions-part-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic Predictions (Part 3)" /><published>2020-05-17T21:12:31-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-17T21:12:31-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/17/pandemic-predictions-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/17/pandemic-predictions-part-3.html">&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another (short) prediction about the long term effects of Coronavirus, along with a call for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s prediction relates to the airlines, and it&amp;rsquo;s closely related to the previous &lt;a href=&quot;http://hirad.ca/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2.html&quot;&gt;prediction around commercial real estate&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, I wanted to include this in that post, but I decided to dig for some data to paint a fuller picture. I failed on that front. If you&amp;rsquo;re good at business/industry analysis and you read this, I have a few asks for you at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the prediction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post, I noted that I expect more and more workplaces to divest of their real estate and for remote work to become much more prevalent. Related to that, I foresee business travel to see a permanent reduction as a result of a much more widely-adopted remote work cultures. I can think of three types of business travel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that requires physical presence in a certain location. For example, a large engineering company may land a construction project far from their HQ and will need to send staff back and forth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work that is more effective in-person. I think this is primarily sales. Building rapport with potential customers is much more effective in person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other. Companies often make people travel due to geographically-constrained workplaces, even though the nature of the work doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; being co-located.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I believe the last category, in the long run, will nearly vanish, as remote work becomes widely adopted and cost savings of less travel become possible and attractive. This will reduce demand for air travel from business customers. Demand will be further reduced in the second category as well - while some work is better done in person, the additional risk factor will move that cutoff line higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where having some data could&amp;rsquo;ve been useful. Given the above predictions, I would like to know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What portion of annual airline revenues come from business travellers and in which sectors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What portion of annual airline &lt;em&gt;profits&lt;/em&gt; come from business travellers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which airlines had the majority of their revenues and profits from business customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In which routes do business travel revenues dominate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given the above information, one could make some further predictions about the airline industry in general. I &lt;em&gt;suspect&lt;/em&gt; that business travellers are less cost conscious than leisure travellers, and that business travellers are less likely to travel on discount airlines than on higher-end airlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a long timeline, I don&amp;rsquo;t think leisure travel will see much permanent reduction in demand. We&amp;rsquo;re not out of the woods yet with COVID19, and even cruise liners are seeing sales recover already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, without more data, these predictions can&amp;rsquo;t say much about how the supply side may change due to the predicted changes in demand. Here&amp;rsquo;s where my ask comes in: if you know where one can obtain the above stats, please get in touch and give me a hand - I&amp;rsquo;m flying blind here :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">Here&amp;rsquo;s another (short) prediction about the long term effects of Coronavirus, along with a call for help. Today&amp;rsquo;s prediction relates to the airlines, and it&amp;rsquo;s closely related to the previous prediction around commercial real estate. In fact, I wanted to include this in that post, but I decided to dig for some data to paint a fuller picture. I failed on that front. If you&amp;rsquo;re good at business/industry analysis and you read this, I have a few asks for you at the end. For the prediction: In the previous post, I noted that I expect more and more workplaces to divest of their real estate and for remote work to become much more prevalent. Related to that, I foresee business travel to see a permanent reduction as a result of a much more widely-adopted remote work cultures. I can think of three types of business travel: Work that requires physical presence in a certain location. For example, a large engineering company may land a construction project far from their HQ and will need to send staff back and forth. Work that is more effective in-person. I think this is primarily sales. Building rapport with potential customers is much more effective in person. Other. Companies often make people travel due to geographically-constrained workplaces, even though the nature of the work doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily require being co-located. I believe the last category, in the long run, will nearly vanish, as remote work becomes widely adopted and cost savings of less travel become possible and attractive. This will reduce demand for air travel from business customers. Demand will be further reduced in the second category as well - while some work is better done in person, the additional risk factor will move that cutoff line higher. Here&amp;rsquo;s where having some data could&amp;rsquo;ve been useful. Given the above predictions, I would like to know: What portion of annual airline revenues come from business travellers and in which sectors? What portion of annual airline profits come from business travellers? Which airlines had the majority of their revenues and profits from business customers? In which routes do business travel revenues dominate? Given the above information, one could make some further predictions about the airline industry in general. I suspect that business travellers are less cost conscious than leisure travellers, and that business travellers are less likely to travel on discount airlines than on higher-end airlines. On a long timeline, I don&amp;rsquo;t think leisure travel will see much permanent reduction in demand. We&amp;rsquo;re not out of the woods yet with COVID19, and even cruise liners are seeing sales recover already. Unfortunately, without more data, these predictions can&amp;rsquo;t say much about how the supply side may change due to the predicted changes in demand. Here&amp;rsquo;s where my ask comes in: if you know where one can obtain the above stats, please get in touch and give me a hand - I&amp;rsquo;m flying blind here :)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic Predictions (Part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic Predictions (Part 2)" /><published>2020-05-02T15:26:35-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-02T15:26:35-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/05/02/pandemic-predictions-part-2.html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hirad.ca/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about when we might go back to normal. Today, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what possible long-term ramifications the COVID19 pandemic might have. It would be an interesting thought exercise to do this for a variety of economic sectors. For this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll start with the most obvious long term impact: the impact on commercial real estate. This first became obvious to me about a week or two into North America being hit, and it has been pointed out by a number of writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a living post - I will update it as I think this through more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prediction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think commercial real estate is going to see a permanent drop in demand and therefore in prices. This does not hold true for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; types of commercial real estate, but it does hold true for many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My Reasoning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An anecdote: my company recently got acquired by a bank. When we joined them, just a few months ago, people steeped in bank culture found the idea of remote work not only alien, but somewhat disturbing. On the other hand, walking 20-30 minutes between multiple towers in downtown Toronto for a meeting is something they don&amp;rsquo;t bat an eye at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2020, there is no legimate reason why business needs to be conducted that way - specially in technology-focused businesses. This was not a failure of capability, as much as it was a failure of culture. Coronavirus has shattered that culture. Everyone at those offices is now working from home. This is not to say that everyone &lt;em&gt;likes&lt;/em&gt; working from home right now (I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed having children is a particular impediment in enjoying WFH). But they&amp;rsquo;ve all been forced into a mandatory two-month-long trial, which is likely to continue. It&amp;rsquo;s a similar story across all sorts of businesses, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we&amp;rsquo;re through this pandemic, I expect everyone to return to business-as-usual. But I expect some key lessons will be learned from this about the benefits of remote work in cultures that would otherwise never imagine it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic is over, more workplaces will be offering remote work options for more types of roles. With this, lack of remote work options will become an impediment to hiring top talent, as it already has for tech hires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the pandemic is over, many workplaces will be reviewing how much they got done with everyone working from home, and they&amp;rsquo;ll be eyeing the expense line on their cash flows as a top candidate for cost-cutting. Even workplaces that are primarily office-based may need a reduced capacity as some portion of their workforce can work remotely at any given time. Large corporations that own their own real estate may see it as less essential and will be more likely to divest, increasing supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture shifts take time to be ingrained, but the pandemic has massively accelerated the shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of office space, many businesses will be innovating with a lower reliance on expensive, prime real estate. Cloud kitchens, for example, were a trend pre-pandemic, and that will only continue. If Amazon had habituated us to buy things online and get them a few days later, pandemic will take this to the next level, with delivery of all essentials becoming not just a preference, but a matter of safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big impediment to remote work is legal. When I bought my apartment, I had to commute for approx. 45 minutes to a lawyer&amp;rsquo;s office, sign a few documents in front of her (which took 5 minutes), then commute back for 45 minutes. This was and is infuriarting and nobody should accept it as &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;okay&amp;rsquo;. We have better ways, and the pandemic has also set the stage for updating our legal frameworks to be more remote-friendly – changes that would otherwise move at a glacial pace. For now, many of these changes are poised as temporary measures, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it&amp;rsquo;ll start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these factors will conspire to decrease the demand in commercial real estate. You&amp;rsquo;ve heard about the obvious winners in the current circumstance: remote communication tools, e-commerce, to name a few. This is the flipside of that coin - commercial real estate is the obvious loser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to be spending less time in wasteful commutes, and more time getting shit done. We&amp;rsquo;ll be happier, and in the very long term, we may even have more beautiful, less car-focused, more environmentally-friendly, and more decentralized cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The impact of this change on the urban landscape is another very interesting thread - to be pulled on in another post perhaps.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all types of commercial real estate will see this drop in demand, of course. As we spend more time in our homes, and more time away from a &amp;ldquo;downtown core&amp;rdquo;, we&amp;rsquo;ll need increasingly better infrastructure to serve our needs where we are. Many services that are currently concentrated in business districts will be downsized and spread more evenly across the urban landscape, closer to where people live.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html">In the previous post, I talked about when we might go back to normal. Today, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what possible long-term ramifications the COVID19 pandemic might have. It would be an interesting thought exercise to do this for a variety of economic sectors. For this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll start with the most obvious long term impact: the impact on commercial real estate. This first became obvious to me about a week or two into North America being hit, and it has been pointed out by a number of writers. This is a living post - I will update it as I think this through more deeply. Prediction I think commercial real estate is going to see a permanent drop in demand and therefore in prices. This does not hold true for all types of commercial real estate, but it does hold true for many. My Reasoning An anecdote: my company recently got acquired by a bank. When we joined them, just a few months ago, people steeped in bank culture found the idea of remote work not only alien, but somewhat disturbing. On the other hand, walking 20-30 minutes between multiple towers in downtown Toronto for a meeting is something they don&amp;rsquo;t bat an eye at. In 2020, there is no legimate reason why business needs to be conducted that way - specially in technology-focused businesses. This was not a failure of capability, as much as it was a failure of culture. Coronavirus has shattered that culture. Everyone at those offices is now working from home. This is not to say that everyone likes working from home right now (I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed having children is a particular impediment in enjoying WFH). But they&amp;rsquo;ve all been forced into a mandatory two-month-long trial, which is likely to continue. It&amp;rsquo;s a similar story across all sorts of businesses, of course. Once we&amp;rsquo;re through this pandemic, I expect everyone to return to business-as-usual. But I expect some key lessons will be learned from this about the benefits of remote work in cultures that would otherwise never imagine it. When the pandemic is over, more workplaces will be offering remote work options for more types of roles. With this, lack of remote work options will become an impediment to hiring top talent, as it already has for tech hires. When the pandemic is over, many workplaces will be reviewing how much they got done with everyone working from home, and they&amp;rsquo;ll be eyeing the expense line on their cash flows as a top candidate for cost-cutting. Even workplaces that are primarily office-based may need a reduced capacity as some portion of their workforce can work remotely at any given time. Large corporations that own their own real estate may see it as less essential and will be more likely to divest, increasing supply. Culture shifts take time to be ingrained, but the pandemic has massively accelerated the shift. Outside of office space, many businesses will be innovating with a lower reliance on expensive, prime real estate. Cloud kitchens, for example, were a trend pre-pandemic, and that will only continue. If Amazon had habituated us to buy things online and get them a few days later, pandemic will take this to the next level, with delivery of all essentials becoming not just a preference, but a matter of safety. One big impediment to remote work is legal. When I bought my apartment, I had to commute for approx. 45 minutes to a lawyer&amp;rsquo;s office, sign a few documents in front of her (which took 5 minutes), then commute back for 45 minutes. This was and is infuriarting and nobody should accept it as &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;okay&amp;rsquo;. We have better ways, and the pandemic has also set the stage for updating our legal frameworks to be more remote-friendly – changes that would otherwise move at a glacial pace. For now, many of these changes are poised as temporary measures, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it&amp;rsquo;ll start. All of these factors will conspire to decrease the demand in commercial real estate. You&amp;rsquo;ve heard about the obvious winners in the current circumstance: remote communication tools, e-commerce, to name a few. This is the flipside of that coin - commercial real estate is the obvious loser. We&amp;rsquo;re going to be spending less time in wasteful commutes, and more time getting shit done. We&amp;rsquo;ll be happier, and in the very long term, we may even have more beautiful, less car-focused, more environmentally-friendly, and more decentralized cities. (The impact of this change on the urban landscape is another very interesting thread - to be pulled on in another post perhaps.) Not all types of commercial real estate will see this drop in demand, of course. As we spend more time in our homes, and more time away from a &amp;ldquo;downtown core&amp;rdquo;, we&amp;rsquo;ll need increasingly better infrastructure to serve our needs where we are. Many services that are currently concentrated in business districts will be downsized and spread more evenly across the urban landscape, closer to where people live.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic Predictions (Part 1)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic Predictions (Part 1)" /><published>2020-04-26T18:19:30-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T18:19:30-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2020/04/26/pandemic-predictions-part-1.html">&lt;p&gt;Like everyone else, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a number of conversation in the last few weeks around the question of &amp;ldquo;when will we go back to normal?&amp;rdquo;. So here&amp;rsquo;s how I think we need to approach the answer, based on my readings so far. The TL;DR is &amp;ldquo;not soon&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to understand why this virus is problematic. It&amp;rsquo;s not just that the disease is so bad. Even though it is bad, we can treat most people who get it. The main issue is that it&amp;rsquo;s spreading so fast, and that means overwhelming the healthcare system. Medicine may &amp;ldquo;know&amp;rdquo; how to help someone, but if there are no doctors or hospital beds or other equipment to deliver the treatment, the knowledge does us no good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the main risk is overloading the health care system. Therefore, &amp;ldquo;when will we go back to normal&amp;rdquo; is really asking &amp;ldquo;when can we do everything we used to do, without running the risk of overloading the health care system?&amp;rdquo;. That question in turn is really asking &amp;ldquo;when will we be confident there won&amp;rsquo;t be a surge of infections from our day-to-day activities?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to be confident of that there won&amp;rsquo;t be a surge, one of the following must be true:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a vaccine. This is, in the best case, 1.5-2 years out. Additionally, once a vaccine exists, it must be manufactured in sufficiently large quantities. Likely, it&amp;rsquo;ll have gradual rollout, and that will take time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have herd immunity. This is also either very slow (order of years) or very catastrophic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have a treatment. A vaccine is not strictly neccessary, if we can find treatments that won&amp;rsquo;t require prolonged, intense hospitalizations for the most-affected patients. I haven&amp;rsquo;t read anything about this, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how likely it is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have pervasive and fast testing. Having this requires competent planning and execution. We seem to be in a pretty good place on that front in Canada and specially in BC. However, this path also requires access to equipment/manufacturing capacity, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if we can get that in Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;From what I can tell, barring some miraculous breakthrough, achieving any of these solutions at a sufficiently large scale is an effort in the order of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming we have one of these options available, we must subtract from this asset any liability that will put its gains at risk. For example&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will individuals who have had the virus be able to get sick from it again? (The fact that we don&amp;rsquo;t know this six months later should give a sense of the timeline before we can get a handle on it.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the Canadian government buckle under some political pressure &amp;amp; open the border with the USA? If that happens, we can have American pee in our pool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will we allow foreign travel/tourism? Again, if we&amp;rsquo;re doing well locally, but we don&amp;rsquo;t have closed borders, we can be inviting the virus from abroad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the &amp;ldquo;solution&amp;rdquo; we come up with be optional or mandatory? If we find a vaccine tomorrow, how many hicks will refuse to vaccinate to avoid autism, for example? If we do pervasive testing, can some people opt-out and yet go about their day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All of this is to say, I doubt we&amp;rsquo;re going back to normal any time soon, not for years - until we have a vaccine and/or herd immunity. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we&amp;rsquo;ll be in lockdown or staying home the whole time. I think the most likely scenario – the option that seems most immediately available – is that we will cycle through periods of lockdown and relaxing restrictions. We won&amp;rsquo;t really flatten the curve, we&amp;rsquo;ll break it down into several smaller curves over a longer time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things, like international travel or large-crowd events (concerts, sports), will be the last to make a come back. Other activities can come back more quickly. We may be able to hang out in small groups. Some public spaces may be able to open with some restrictions (like mandatory masks). Some workplaces may be able to operate in-person again (should they still want to). And I sure hope BC will open its provincial parks again. But we should not hope to go back to living the way we used to any time soon. In fact, we probably never will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long period of living under restrictions will re-shape society. We will find new ways of doing the things we did before, and we may find that the new ways are, in some cases, not so bad. For example, more people will work from home permanently. This will have widespread ramifications for the economy. I &lt;em&gt;hope&lt;/em&gt; to follow up with additional posts on how I think this situation will affect different industries. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Like everyone else, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a number of conversation in the last few weeks around the question of &amp;ldquo;when will we go back to normal?&amp;rdquo;. So here&amp;rsquo;s how I think we need to approach the answer, based on my readings so far. The TL;DR is &amp;ldquo;not soon&amp;rdquo;.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Trust the Peacock</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/11/12/dont-trust-the-peacock.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don't Trust the Peacock" /><published>2018-11-12T17:44:58-08:00</published><updated>2018-11-12T17:44:58-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/11/12/dont-trust-the-peacock</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/11/12/dont-trust-the-peacock.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the great Tao is forgotten,
goodness and piety appear.
When the body&amp;rsquo;s intelligence declines,
cleverness and knowledge step forth.
When there is no peace in the family,
filial piety begins.
When the country falls into chaos,
patriotism is born.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- &lt;strong&gt;Lao Tzu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say judging people is bad. I’m not sure I agree. Regardless, we all do it anyway. I want to continuously improve my heuristics to make good judgements of people. Good heuristics are rare, but I have one that’s fairly reliable that I’m going to share with you here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last year, I attended a ten day meditation retreat. There was one specific individual at this retreat who stood out. He was an “old student”, which means he had done at least one ten-day course before. While the attendees were socializing at the meditation centre before the beginning of the course and before Noble Silence was to be observed, he was sitting quietly in a corner. If someone tried to speak to him, he would turn his head toward them extremely slowly, give the shortest possible answer, and go back to being quiet. In addition to his behaviour, he also stood out because of his appearance. He was wearing what looked like rags — what you might expect to see on a beggar on an Indian street. Except it didn’t look authentic. The rags were quite nice. It was what you might expect to see from a well-off white guy impersonating a poor Indian beggar. He also walked barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time I noticed him was on the last day of the retreat. For ten days, we had all been silent. On the last day, Noble Silence ended and people started chattering again. However, talking was still disallowed in the main meditation hall. At one point, while some people were talking in the hallway, I was in the meditation hall, trying to practice. This individual was also there, sitting a few rows in front of me. In between us, two people started talking. The meditation hall was already not so quiet, considering that the chatter from the hallway was easily audible. The additional noise from the two talkers inside the hall was too much for this individual to bear. He turned around and gave the two talkers an angry “SSSSHHHHH!!!”. I’ll never forget the look of rage on his face. Ten days of working on increasing compassion had evaporated in an instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This individual, in my mind, represents the quintessential “peacock” in a community. He went to great lengths to put on appearances about his devotion to the practice, but at the end of the day, he exhibited none of the skill. Peacocks exist in every walk of life, and observing many of them has led me to this heuristic: I am instantly suspicious of people who are putting on excessive appearances. These appearances can be visual (eg. clothing) or behavioural (eg. acting overly sensitive to certain subjects) or verbal (eg. the proverbial “blowing of one’s own trumpet”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this peacocking is to elevate one’s status in a community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peacocks thrive in environments where the authenticity of status signals are hard to gauge. In the tech community, peacocking is difficult. You can’t fool people into thinking you’re a good engineer by putting on thicker glasses and lowering your social skills. At the end of the day, you’ll have to speak knowledgeably and write good code. Nassim Taleb has pointed out in &lt;em&gt;Skin In The Game&lt;/em&gt;, the ultimate authentic signal is courage: a display of courage &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; proof of its true existence. Most signals that people send each other don’t have this high of a signal-to-substance ratio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, zouk and aikido communities that I’m part of are rife with peacocks. In zouk, these people gravitate toward a style of dance that (they think) does not require rigorous work on fundamentals. They might state that feeling is more important than technique. They might wear genie pants to look like time-travelling hippies who escaped their commune in the ’60s. The teachers they idolize look this way, so they copy the appearance. Those teachers, however, are often highly skilled, but where their technique might take years of hard practice to copy, their outward appearance can be copied very quickly and used as a status signal in the community. These people often don’t have a regular teacher that they train under, but they attend all the big events and sometimes take private lessons, which they use as an opportunity to &amp;ldquo;socialize&amp;rdquo; with well-known teachers and tell their friends about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In aikido, the story is not so different. Strength and stamina are often used to signal skill in aikido where there is none. Unnecessarily long or elaborate demonstrations are used to impress untrained spectators or equally unskilled peers. The trained eye can see that every technique in these demonstrations is performed with the most egregious mistakes. Often, similar to the zouk peacocks, the aikido peacocks will attend seminars with famous teachers with no attention whatever to the lessons being taught. They love collecting a large catalogue of famous teachers who they can claim they’ve trained under. They might collect photos with these teachers, in which they’ll pose like thugs with a stern face and clenched fists to make sure they look tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to emphasize that merely sending these signals by itself is not evidence of anything wrong. Strength and stamina are not bad things. Attending lots of seminars is not a bad thing. Looking like a hippie&amp;hellip; well, ok, that one’s unforgivable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue with peacocks is not just that they send these signals. It’s that they’re signalling a lie. They want you to believe they possess substance that they simply don’t. Substance is hard to gauge, but we notice others’ signals right away. But here’s the thing about people with substance: they are in no rush and they can wait for you to see theirs. They’re confident and reassured. Peacocks are neither of these things. So when I see someone sending signals a little too loudly, I think the lady doth protest too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heuristics are not perfect, and I try to give people a chance even when my peacock radar is going off. But I’ve often been right about peacocks, and whatever any individual’s merits may be, peacocking is at the very least a sign of disingenuity and perhaps dishonesty. In communities where they can thrive, peacocks will eventually become teachers or leaders, and they will mislead entire contingents of beginners who don’t know any better about choosing who to follow. That is the biggest harm of the peacock.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When the great Tao is forgotten, goodness and piety appear. When the body&amp;rsquo;s intelligence declines, cleverness and knowledge step forth. When there is no peace in the family, filial piety begins. When the country falls into chaos, patriotism is born. - Lao Tzu They say judging people is bad. I’m not sure I agree. Regardless, we all do it anyway. I want to continuously improve my heuristics to make good judgements of people. Good heuristics are rare, but I have one that’s fairly reliable that I’m going to share with you here. Last year, I attended a ten day meditation retreat. There was one specific individual at this retreat who stood out. He was an “old student”, which means he had done at least one ten-day course before. While the attendees were socializing at the meditation centre before the beginning of the course and before Noble Silence was to be observed, he was sitting quietly in a corner. If someone tried to speak to him, he would turn his head toward them extremely slowly, give the shortest possible answer, and go back to being quiet. In addition to his behaviour, he also stood out because of his appearance. He was wearing what looked like rags — what you might expect to see on a beggar on an Indian street. Except it didn’t look authentic. The rags were quite nice. It was what you might expect to see from a well-off white guy impersonating a poor Indian beggar. He also walked barefoot. The next time I noticed him was on the last day of the retreat. For ten days, we had all been silent. On the last day, Noble Silence ended and people started chattering again. However, talking was still disallowed in the main meditation hall. At one point, while some people were talking in the hallway, I was in the meditation hall, trying to practice. This individual was also there, sitting a few rows in front of me. In between us, two people started talking. The meditation hall was already not so quiet, considering that the chatter from the hallway was easily audible. The additional noise from the two talkers inside the hall was too much for this individual to bear. He turned around and gave the two talkers an angry “SSSSHHHHH!!!”. I’ll never forget the look of rage on his face. Ten days of working on increasing compassion had evaporated in an instance. This individual, in my mind, represents the quintessential “peacock” in a community. He went to great lengths to put on appearances about his devotion to the practice, but at the end of the day, he exhibited none of the skill. Peacocks exist in every walk of life, and observing many of them has led me to this heuristic: I am instantly suspicious of people who are putting on excessive appearances. These appearances can be visual (eg. clothing) or behavioural (eg. acting overly sensitive to certain subjects) or verbal (eg. the proverbial “blowing of one’s own trumpet”). The purpose of this peacocking is to elevate one’s status in a community. Peacocks thrive in environments where the authenticity of status signals are hard to gauge. In the tech community, peacocking is difficult. You can’t fool people into thinking you’re a good engineer by putting on thicker glasses and lowering your social skills. At the end of the day, you’ll have to speak knowledgeably and write good code. Nassim Taleb has pointed out in Skin In The Game, the ultimate authentic signal is courage: a display of courage is proof of its true existence. Most signals that people send each other don’t have this high of a signal-to-substance ratio. For example, zouk and aikido communities that I’m part of are rife with peacocks. In zouk, these people gravitate toward a style of dance that (they think) does not require rigorous work on fundamentals. They might state that feeling is more important than technique. They might wear genie pants to look like time-travelling hippies who escaped their commune in the ’60s. The teachers they idolize look this way, so they copy the appearance. Those teachers, however, are often highly skilled, but where their technique might take years of hard practice to copy, their outward appearance can be copied very quickly and used as a status signal in the community. These people often don’t have a regular teacher that they train under, but they attend all the big events and sometimes take private lessons, which they use as an opportunity to &amp;ldquo;socialize&amp;rdquo; with well-known teachers and tell their friends about it. In aikido, the story is not so different. Strength and stamina are often used to signal skill in aikido where there is none. Unnecessarily long or elaborate demonstrations are used to impress untrained spectators or equally unskilled peers. The trained eye can see that every technique in these demonstrations is performed with the most egregious mistakes. Often, similar to the zouk peacocks, the aikido peacocks will attend seminars with famous teachers with no attention whatever to the lessons being taught. They love collecting a large catalogue of famous teachers who they can claim they’ve trained under. They might collect photos with these teachers, in which they’ll pose like thugs with a stern face and clenched fists to make sure they look tough. It’s important to emphasize that merely sending these signals by itself is not evidence of anything wrong. Strength and stamina are not bad things. Attending lots of seminars is not a bad thing. Looking like a hippie&amp;hellip; well, ok, that one’s unforgivable. The issue with peacocks is not just that they send these signals. It’s that they’re signalling a lie. They want you to believe they possess substance that they simply don’t. Substance is hard to gauge, but we notice others’ signals right away. But here’s the thing about people with substance: they are in no rush and they can wait for you to see theirs. They’re confident and reassured. Peacocks are neither of these things. So when I see someone sending signals a little too loudly, I think the lady doth protest too much. Heuristics are not perfect, and I try to give people a chance even when my peacock radar is going off. But I’ve often been right about peacocks, and whatever any individual’s merits may be, peacocking is at the very least a sign of disingenuity and perhaps dishonesty. In communities where they can thrive, peacocks will eventually become teachers or leaders, and they will mislead entire contingents of beginners who don’t know any better about choosing who to follow. That is the biggest harm of the peacock.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goodbye, Old Politics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/10/06/goodbye.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodbye, Old Politics" /><published>2018-10-06T16:48:32-07:00</published><updated>2018-10-06T16:48:32-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/10/06/goodbye</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/10/06/goodbye.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Almost everything here is my takeaway from ideas put forth by Ben Thompson from &lt;a href=&quot;https://stratechery.com&quot;&gt;Stratechery&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://exponent.fm&quot;&gt;Exponent podcast&lt;/a&gt;, being rehashed to cement my own understanding&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world has changed a lot since 90s. Even though I&amp;rsquo;m only 30, I&amp;rsquo;m old enough to remember a time when the world looked very different. I remember fax machines and answering machines that recorded messages on tape. I remember the first computers that grade-school-me would see as nothing more than glorified game consoles. I remember when you had be very mindful of your time on the internet because your ISP was charging you by the kilobyte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the 90s and early 2000s, you had broadcast media with fixed schedules that you had to adapt yourself to, produced by a few big national players; you had big box stores that you&amp;rsquo;d drive to in order to purchase consumer packaged goods from brands that had been established for upwards of a century; and you had a handful of news sources that would tell you more or less the same thing, possibly with a slightly different slant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t have those things anymore. If we do, they&amp;rsquo;re merely a shadow of their old selves, clinging to dear life until their last remnants die with the last generation that doesn&amp;rsquo;t know how to use the internet. Why did these things go away?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central theme is that the internet allowed a shift from a world where the winners controlled the supply, to a world where the winners control demand. The few media companies that controlled the narrative surrounding the news before the internet didn&amp;rsquo;t do so because theirs was the only narrative people wanted to read or hear. They did so because they owned printing presses and trucks and it was far too expensive for anybody else to compete with them. The consumer packaged goods that you would buy from the likes of, say, Gillette weren&amp;rsquo;t there because they were the best product on the market, they were there because the manufacturers had the best deals with the big box retailers and could effectively block anyone else from entering the market. Shelf space was limited and they controlled it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; try to get your own competing products built with a higher quality or a lower price, but good luck to you for getting it to the market. Similarly, your cable or phone company was not entrenched thanks to consumer choice but because they owned precious limited infrastructure that nobody else could use, so consumers had no choice but to accept their poor service at outrageous prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this was even true of the technology companies of the 80s and 90s. Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s dominance was built around it being difficult for consumers to be able to use the tools they wanted on any platform other than Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet changed all of this. It made distribution essentially free, so all of these industries that were predicated on monopolized distribution channels began to lose their grip. In the case of Microsoft, for example, the tools people really wanted were now one layer of abstraction above the chokepoint – you can access the information on the internet through any device regardless of whether it runs Windows or not. For the consumer packaged goods industry, online distribution meant that they were now on a level playing field with &lt;em&gt;anyone&lt;/em&gt; who could produce the same product at them and deliver them to the consumers' homes. Shelf space was unlimited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the last decade has been one of distribution monopolies being sidelined by a new world where their strengths are no longer competitive. What they&amp;rsquo;ve been replaced by are new monopolies. These are monopolies of demand, such as Facebook, Google, or Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t use Facebook, Google, or Amazon because they have to. In fact, you and I are more than free to build and market our own competing products/services to all three (in part courtesy of Amazon and Google services) and market them directly to the same consumers who use them. But it won&amp;rsquo;t make a difference. People won&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to use our service, they&amp;rsquo;ll &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to use theirs because they have network effects. You can build an alternative search engine (&lt;a href=&quot;www.bing.com&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.search.yahoo.com&quot;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;www.duckduckgo.com&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt;), but Google&amp;rsquo;s will always work better. You can build your own social network but it won&amp;rsquo;t mean anything because people are already on Facebook (in fact, Google tried and failed). You can still go to any retailer and buy the same old products you see on Amazon, but nobody wants to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This much is clear enough. Where it gets really interesting is when you consider the nearly limitless scope of these changes, and the one most pertinent to the times is the impact of free distribution on politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, at least as long as parties have had votes for their presidential nominees, there has been an understanding that the selection of the nominee is somewhat democratic. In reality that was never the case. While the party base could vote to choose the nominee, they were really only picking one among a handful of candidates pre-selected by the party establishment. If you wanted to win an election, you needed the support of the establishment in securing donors and getting media coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time this changed was before the 2008 election when the preferred Democratic party nominee, Hilary Clinton, got sidelined by a newcomer that used the new media to garner a larger support among the base. Then Trump took that game to a whole new level in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, this is the same pattern we&amp;rsquo;ve observed in multiple other consumer industries. The incumbent monopolies (the big political parties) held the choke point for reaching the masses. They controlled the supply (access to money, which then bought media). You could run for office on your own, but you weren&amp;rsquo;t gonna get very far. The parties' monopoly has now been subverted by the internet. Distribution is now free – anybody can reach the populace just as well as anyone else on social media – and what matters is who controls demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewed in this light, the current political situation in the US is both unsurprising and an inevitability. Any expectation that we will go back to the good old days of &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; politics are foolish. The entire paradigm has shifted and new actors (no pun intended) who can navigate the new world are going to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every distruption brought about by the internet, this will be a double-edged sword. While this disruption of the old order has led to some chaos (and will continue to do so until we figure out how to navigate the new paradigm skillfully), there is now &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; room for innovation in politics Admittedly, this may take some time. Personally, I don&amp;rsquo;t think Trump is going to be the final iteration of this change. When Facebook and Google disrupted old school mass advertising, they may have eaten the lunch of the old media, but they also made possible entire new industries that couldn&amp;rsquo;t have existed in the world of the old media. Today you can have successful Kickstarter campaigns that turn into new businesses with the support of a few tens or hundreds of thousands of people. In the old world, an ad campaign that only converted 20,000 customers would be an utter failure, given the cost of reaching them and distributing the goods to them. In the modern world, virtual mom-and-pop business can be started over night by targetting a narrow niche of just that size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major obstacle I see to this innovation is the marriage of politics to physical geography. On the internet, niche markets can be targetted because they&amp;rsquo;re not constrained by the physical world. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what the answer is here (perhaps Peter Thiel&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/floating-city-plans-seasteading-institute-peter-thiel-blue-frontiers-2017-12#at-the-same-time-rising-sea-levels-due-to-climate-change-threaten-coastal-cities-around-the-world-building-a-floating-city-could-be-one-option-for-tackling-that-14&quot;&gt;floating cities&lt;/a&gt;). The only thing I&amp;rsquo;m sure of is that there&amp;rsquo;s no going back to the old paradigm, and we can expect this new paradigm to become ever more pervasive: across more levels of government and across more governments.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Almost everything here is my takeaway from ideas put forth by Ben Thompson from Stratechery and the Exponent podcast, being rehashed to cement my own understanding. The world has changed a lot since 90s. Even though I&amp;rsquo;m only 30, I&amp;rsquo;m old enough to remember a time when the world looked very different. I remember fax machines and answering machines that recorded messages on tape. I remember the first computers that grade-school-me would see as nothing more than glorified game consoles. I remember when you had be very mindful of your time on the internet because your ISP was charging you by the kilobyte. In the 90s and early 2000s, you had broadcast media with fixed schedules that you had to adapt yourself to, produced by a few big national players; you had big box stores that you&amp;rsquo;d drive to in order to purchase consumer packaged goods from brands that had been established for upwards of a century; and you had a handful of news sources that would tell you more or less the same thing, possibly with a slightly different slant. We don&amp;rsquo;t have those things anymore. If we do, they&amp;rsquo;re merely a shadow of their old selves, clinging to dear life until their last remnants die with the last generation that doesn&amp;rsquo;t know how to use the internet. Why did these things go away? The central theme is that the internet allowed a shift from a world where the winners controlled the supply, to a world where the winners control demand. The few media companies that controlled the narrative surrounding the news before the internet didn&amp;rsquo;t do so because theirs was the only narrative people wanted to read or hear. They did so because they owned printing presses and trucks and it was far too expensive for anybody else to compete with them. The consumer packaged goods that you would buy from the likes of, say, Gillette weren&amp;rsquo;t there because they were the best product on the market, they were there because the manufacturers had the best deals with the big box retailers and could effectively block anyone else from entering the market. Shelf space was limited and they controlled it. You could try to get your own competing products built with a higher quality or a lower price, but good luck to you for getting it to the market. Similarly, your cable or phone company was not entrenched thanks to consumer choice but because they owned precious limited infrastructure that nobody else could use, so consumers had no choice but to accept their poor service at outrageous prices. Interestingly, this was even true of the technology companies of the 80s and 90s. Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s dominance was built around it being difficult for consumers to be able to use the tools they wanted on any platform other than Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s. The internet changed all of this. It made distribution essentially free, so all of these industries that were predicated on monopolized distribution channels began to lose their grip. In the case of Microsoft, for example, the tools people really wanted were now one layer of abstraction above the chokepoint – you can access the information on the internet through any device regardless of whether it runs Windows or not. For the consumer packaged goods industry, online distribution meant that they were now on a level playing field with anyone who could produce the same product at them and deliver them to the consumers' homes. Shelf space was unlimited. The story of the last decade has been one of distribution monopolies being sidelined by a new world where their strengths are no longer competitive. What they&amp;rsquo;ve been replaced by are new monopolies. These are monopolies of demand, such as Facebook, Google, or Amazon. People don&amp;rsquo;t use Facebook, Google, or Amazon because they have to. In fact, you and I are more than free to build and market our own competing products/services to all three (in part courtesy of Amazon and Google services) and market them directly to the same consumers who use them. But it won&amp;rsquo;t make a difference. People won&amp;rsquo;t want to use our service, they&amp;rsquo;ll want to use theirs because they have network effects. You can build an alternative search engine (there are many), but Google&amp;rsquo;s will always work better. You can build your own social network but it won&amp;rsquo;t mean anything because people are already on Facebook (in fact, Google tried and failed). You can still go to any retailer and buy the same old products you see on Amazon, but nobody wants to do that. This much is clear enough. Where it gets really interesting is when you consider the nearly limitless scope of these changes, and the one most pertinent to the times is the impact of free distribution on politics. In the US, at least as long as parties have had votes for their presidential nominees, there has been an understanding that the selection of the nominee is somewhat democratic. In reality that was never the case. While the party base could vote to choose the nominee, they were really only picking one among a handful of candidates pre-selected by the party establishment. If you wanted to win an election, you needed the support of the establishment in securing donors and getting media coverage. The first time this changed was before the 2008 election when the preferred Democratic party nominee, Hilary Clinton, got sidelined by a newcomer that used the new media to garner a larger support among the base. Then Trump took that game to a whole new level in 2016. In a sense, this is the same pattern we&amp;rsquo;ve observed in multiple other consumer industries. The incumbent monopolies (the big political parties) held the choke point for reaching the masses. They controlled the supply (access to money, which then bought media). You could run for office on your own, but you weren&amp;rsquo;t gonna get very far. The parties' monopoly has now been subverted by the internet. Distribution is now free – anybody can reach the populace just as well as anyone else on social media – and what matters is who controls demand. Viewed in this light, the current political situation in the US is both unsurprising and an inevitability. Any expectation that we will go back to the good old days of &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; politics are foolish. The entire paradigm has shifted and new actors (no pun intended) who can navigate the new world are going to win. Like every distruption brought about by the internet, this will be a double-edged sword. While this disruption of the old order has led to some chaos (and will continue to do so until we figure out how to navigate the new paradigm skillfully), there is now some room for innovation in politics Admittedly, this may take some time. Personally, I don&amp;rsquo;t think Trump is going to be the final iteration of this change. When Facebook and Google disrupted old school mass advertising, they may have eaten the lunch of the old media, but they also made possible entire new industries that couldn&amp;rsquo;t have existed in the world of the old media. Today you can have successful Kickstarter campaigns that turn into new businesses with the support of a few tens or hundreds of thousands of people. In the old world, an ad campaign that only converted 20,000 customers would be an utter failure, given the cost of reaching them and distributing the goods to them. In the modern world, virtual mom-and-pop business can be started over night by targetting a narrow niche of just that size. The major obstacle I see to this innovation is the marriage of politics to physical geography. On the internet, niche markets can be targetted because they&amp;rsquo;re not constrained by the physical world. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what the answer is here (perhaps Peter Thiel&amp;rsquo;s floating cities). The only thing I&amp;rsquo;m sure of is that there&amp;rsquo;s no going back to the old paradigm, and we can expect this new paradigm to become ever more pervasive: across more levels of government and across more governments.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Master’s Work is Invisible</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/02/02/the-masters-work-is-invisible.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Master's Work is Invisible" /><published>2018-02-02T23:15:48-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-02T23:15:48-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/02/02/the-masters-work-is-invisible</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/02/02/the-masters-work-is-invisible.html">&lt;p&gt;“Why are you squeezing my arms!? It’s way too much force! It needs to be much more subtle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been taking dance lessons for several months and I was now getting into the difficult stuff. In this lesson, I had to learn to guide my partner’s head while softly holding the hands. It was not easy. As a beginner, I had watched experienced dancers do this many times before and it made perfect sense - like a mechanical inevitability. Reproducing it was a different story. I was doing my best to copy the shape I had observed the teacher make, but the technique required a much more intricate movement than what I could observe. Before I could do this movement, I had to &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; how it worked rather than observe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a theme that comes up often when one is learning something new. To the non-practitioner, things either look too mysterious, magical, and overwhelming, or they look much simpler than they actually are. Rarely can the non-practitioner dissect the elements that make the end result great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this situation, there are two erroneous reaction that outside observers or novice practitioners have when they observe a master:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re overwhelmed by the master&amp;rsquo;s achievement and they can&amp;rsquo;t fathom the steps that would take them to the same level of mastery. This kind of thinking leads them to undue admiration of the master or simply giving up the pursuit in desperation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They attribute the overall success to one small component that they &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; understand. This, in turn, leads them to either belittle the overall accomplishment by claiming that the one understandable component is not that special, or, if they are novice practitioners trying to reproduce the master’s result, they might focus on doing more of the thing they can understand. With time and attention, however, the practitioner’s field of vision expands to detect more of the nuance and the intricacies. Their attention during practice can then shift to the new areas that they’ve become aware of. This is how they can approach mastery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Imagine that a master chef begins using a rare ingredient in a new recipe. He does this because he understands how this ingredient interacts with all the others and the impact it might have, considering its place in the meal among the other courses. A less skilled chef who’s aspiring to be great may see this, and he may decide he wants to use the exact same ingredient. But since his understanding of the ingredient and its place in the big picture is not as comprehensive as the master’s, he might use this ingredient in a way that is jarring to his patron or not as well considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, a second type of error can occur in outside observers. Let’s say the less skilled chef is the first to pioneer this rare ingredient. While he might score some points for boldness, his output is still commensurate to his skill level. If the master chef then adopts this new ingredient in his own recipe, an untrained outside observer may fault him for being a copycat. The urge to do this among people who are not experts is particularly strong due to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tall_poppy_syndrome&quot;&gt;tall poppy syndrome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got thinking about this after the last product announcements from Apple. As they always do after an event like this, the detractors came out in droves to explain how Apple had built things that were available in Samsung products earlier. What these detractors miss is that the individual features that they’re focusing on are akin to ingredients in a recipe. We don’t set our expectations for a recipe solely on the basis of the ingredients used in them, but on the basis of who the chef is and their track record. A master chef can use an ingredient tastefully and to great effect. A mediocre one can use the same recipes indiscriminately and with poor results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From martial arts, to technology products, to dance, I’ve observed these two errors in nearly every field I’ve been involved with, it pays to be conscious of them and to detect them in ourselves and others. Misattribute success to one invalid trait and you set your training back by years. Listen to a critic who bases their judgement on bad heuristics and their commentary can cost you more than it helps.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Why are you squeezing my arms!? It’s way too much force! It needs to be much more subtle.” I had been taking dance lessons for several months and I was now getting into the difficult stuff. In this lesson, I had to learn to guide my partner’s head while softly holding the hands. It was not easy. As a beginner, I had watched experienced dancers do this many times before and it made perfect sense - like a mechanical inevitability. Reproducing it was a different story. I was doing my best to copy the shape I had observed the teacher make, but the technique required a much more intricate movement than what I could observe. Before I could do this movement, I had to feel how it worked rather than observe. This is a theme that comes up often when one is learning something new. To the non-practitioner, things either look too mysterious, magical, and overwhelming, or they look much simpler than they actually are. Rarely can the non-practitioner dissect the elements that make the end result great. In this situation, there are two erroneous reaction that outside observers or novice practitioners have when they observe a master: They&amp;rsquo;re overwhelmed by the master&amp;rsquo;s achievement and they can&amp;rsquo;t fathom the steps that would take them to the same level of mastery. This kind of thinking leads them to undue admiration of the master or simply giving up the pursuit in desperation. They attribute the overall success to one small component that they can understand. This, in turn, leads them to either belittle the overall accomplishment by claiming that the one understandable component is not that special, or, if they are novice practitioners trying to reproduce the master’s result, they might focus on doing more of the thing they can understand. With time and attention, however, the practitioner’s field of vision expands to detect more of the nuance and the intricacies. Their attention during practice can then shift to the new areas that they’ve become aware of. This is how they can approach mastery. Imagine that a master chef begins using a rare ingredient in a new recipe. He does this because he understands how this ingredient interacts with all the others and the impact it might have, considering its place in the meal among the other courses. A less skilled chef who’s aspiring to be great may see this, and he may decide he wants to use the exact same ingredient. But since his understanding of the ingredient and its place in the big picture is not as comprehensive as the master’s, he might use this ingredient in a way that is jarring to his patron or not as well considered. Conversely, a second type of error can occur in outside observers. Let’s say the less skilled chef is the first to pioneer this rare ingredient. While he might score some points for boldness, his output is still commensurate to his skill level. If the master chef then adopts this new ingredient in his own recipe, an untrained outside observer may fault him for being a copycat. The urge to do this among people who are not experts is particularly strong due to tall poppy syndrome. I got thinking about this after the last product announcements from Apple. As they always do after an event like this, the detractors came out in droves to explain how Apple had built things that were available in Samsung products earlier. What these detractors miss is that the individual features that they’re focusing on are akin to ingredients in a recipe. We don’t set our expectations for a recipe solely on the basis of the ingredients used in them, but on the basis of who the chef is and their track record. A master chef can use an ingredient tastefully and to great effect. A mediocre one can use the same recipes indiscriminately and with poor results. From martial arts, to technology products, to dance, I’ve observed these two errors in nearly every field I’ve been involved with, it pays to be conscious of them and to detect them in ourselves and others. Misattribute success to one invalid trait and you set your training back by years. Listen to a critic who bases their judgement on bad heuristics and their commentary can cost you more than it helps.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Extreme Self-Responsibility</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/01/20/extreme-self-responsibility.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Extreme Self-Responsibility" /><published>2018-01-20T07:40:55-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-20T07:40:55-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/01/20/extreme-self-responsibility</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/01/20/extreme-self-responsibility.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the most impactful books I read in my early 20s was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/79352.Six_Pillars_of_Self_Esteem&quot;&gt;The Six Pillars of Self-Esteem&lt;/a&gt; by clinical psychologist, Nathaniel Branden. It was a prescription for living a good life, long before I had learned about stoicism or meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In Branden’s view self-esteem is our competence in life. It is the confidence that we can take on the challenges of life and be successful and that we are deserving of that success. Additionally, self-esteem doesn’t exist in a vacuum. It’s something that can be cultivated through deliberate practice, and it leads to a virtuous cycle: deliberate practice makes one more competent, the result of the competence increases one’s self-esteem, which makes the practice easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the core components of self-esteem is the practice of self-responsibility. Self-responsibility is the sense of control over one’s own life and actions. According to Branden, self-responsibility entails the following realizations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for the achievement of my desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for my choices and actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for the level of consciousness I bring to my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for the level of consciousness I bring to my relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for my behavior with other people – coworkers, associates, customers, spouse, children, friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for how I prioritize my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for the quality of my communications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for my personal happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for accepting or choosing the values by which I live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am responsible for raising my self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the part of the book that stuck with me the most. It is an incredibly empowering concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if we take this practice to an extreme?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When things don’t go our way, it is far too easy for our minds to construct elaborate excuses and find a scapegoat. This is when we begin to resent others, or hate the world/god for what it has done to us. We can avoid this trap if we simply take responsibility for… everything. Did I have a fight with a friend? I am responsible for that. Are things going poorly at work? I am responsible for that. Have I not achieved my goals? I am responsible for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But that’s impossible.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s more possible than you’d think. In talking to friends and family about this subject, I’ve found the main objection to the idea of extreme self-responsibility to be naive ideas around “fairness”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some adverse event occurs and we immediately lament that it was not fair that &lt;em&gt;it happened to us&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, what we can do is to a) try to pinpoint how our own actions led to that outcome, and b) see what we can do to alleviate the situation given that it has already occurred. This shifts the narrative from a sense of victimhood (“things are happening to me”) to a sense of empowerment (“I make things happen”). Being responsible for things and those things being fair are totally unrelated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But I thought you went to a meditation retreat and are all about acceptance.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems living well is accepting what is outside of our control, and making an honest effort in improving that which is under our control. Extreme self-responsibility simply expands the domain of control. It is a mental hack to counteract our mind’s brilliance in taking the lazy way out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-responsibility does not mean that unfortunate events are &lt;em&gt;your fault&lt;/em&gt;. It means that regardless of whose fault it is, it is within your power to influence things that are important to you/your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, it may have been unfair that you had a mean math teacher in grade 10, who discouraged you from learning math for the rest of your life. But if you now deem math to be something helpful, you are responsible for overcoming that. Or it may be true that you had an unfortunate childhood that left you with many emotional baggages that make life harder now. But regardless, you are responsible for moving toward your goals and either overcome or work around those limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In psychology there is a concept called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Locus_of_control&quot;&gt;locus of control&lt;/a&gt;”. It measures how much people feel they have control over their own lives. People with an external locus of control are those who believe things happen &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; them. People with an internal locus of control are those who believe they can &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; things happen. Having an internal locus of control is associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/moments-matter/201708/locus-control&quot;&gt;greater motivation&lt;/a&gt; and drive and higher resiliency in the face of adversity. (This why an internal locus of control is highly correlated with entrepreneurship). Having an external locus of control is associated with higher anxiety and &lt;a href=&quot;http://psycnet.apa.org/record/1988-35828-001&quot;&gt;greater susceptibility to depression&lt;/a&gt;. Extreme self-responsibility is a practice for shifting one’s locus of control inward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I’d be remiss if I didn’t point out that this philosophy runs in total opposition to the currently prevalent culture of victimhood. Instead of raising responsible, high self-esteem kids that trust their own competence in life, so many schools and universities are running in the direction of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/22/opinion/sunday/judith-shulevitz-hiding-from-scary-ideas.html&quot;&gt;protecting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/grade-point/wp/2016/03/24/someone-wrote-trump-2016-on-emorys-campus-in-chalk-some-students-said-they-no-longer-feel-safe/?utm_term=.714d88d65bbc&quot;&gt;everyone&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/10/11/magazine/why-are-more-american-teenagers-than-ever-suffering-from-severe-anxiety.html&quot;&gt;against&lt;/a&gt; the most minute slight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aversion to anything that may be remotely unpleasant  eliminates any sense of self-responsibility, and it raises impotent adults who are taught they’re unequipped to face the world as it is. In this way, victimhood culture worsens the lives of the very people it feigns compassion for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, let us put our own house in order first. Extreme self-responsibility is something I had lost focus on for a long time, and I wanted to write about it as a refresher. I’m trying to put a renewed focus on this going forward.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One of the most impactful books I read in my early 20s was The Six Pillars of Self-Esteem by clinical psychologist, Nathaniel Branden. It was a prescription for living a good life, long before I had learned about stoicism or meditation. In Branden’s view self-esteem is our competence in life. It is the confidence that we can take on the challenges of life and be successful and that we are deserving of that success. Additionally, self-esteem doesn’t exist in a vacuum. It’s something that can be cultivated through deliberate practice, and it leads to a virtuous cycle: deliberate practice makes one more competent, the result of the competence increases one’s self-esteem, which makes the practice easier. One of the core components of self-esteem is the practice of self-responsibility. Self-responsibility is the sense of control over one’s own life and actions. According to Branden, self-responsibility entails the following realizations: I am responsible for the achievement of my desires. I am responsible for my choices and actions. I am responsible for the level of consciousness I bring to my work. I am responsible for the level of consciousness I bring to my relationships. I am responsible for my behavior with other people – coworkers, associates, customers, spouse, children, friends. I am responsible for how I prioritize my time. I am responsible for the quality of my communications. I am responsible for my personal happiness. I am responsible for accepting or choosing the values by which I live. I am responsible for raising my self-esteem. This was the part of the book that stuck with me the most. It is an incredibly empowering concept. What if we take this practice to an extreme? When things don’t go our way, it is far too easy for our minds to construct elaborate excuses and find a scapegoat. This is when we begin to resent others, or hate the world/god for what it has done to us. We can avoid this trap if we simply take responsibility for… everything. Did I have a fight with a friend? I am responsible for that. Are things going poorly at work? I am responsible for that. Have I not achieved my goals? I am responsible for that. “But that’s impossible.” It’s more possible than you’d think. In talking to friends and family about this subject, I’ve found the main objection to the idea of extreme self-responsibility to be naive ideas around “fairness”. Some adverse event occurs and we immediately lament that it was not fair that it happened to us. Instead, what we can do is to a) try to pinpoint how our own actions led to that outcome, and b) see what we can do to alleviate the situation given that it has already occurred. This shifts the narrative from a sense of victimhood (“things are happening to me”) to a sense of empowerment (“I make things happen”). Being responsible for things and those things being fair are totally unrelated. “But I thought you went to a meditation retreat and are all about acceptance.” It seems living well is accepting what is outside of our control, and making an honest effort in improving that which is under our control. Extreme self-responsibility simply expands the domain of control. It is a mental hack to counteract our mind’s brilliance in taking the lazy way out. Self-responsibility does not mean that unfortunate events are your fault. It means that regardless of whose fault it is, it is within your power to influence things that are important to you/your life. For example, it may have been unfair that you had a mean math teacher in grade 10, who discouraged you from learning math for the rest of your life. But if you now deem math to be something helpful, you are responsible for overcoming that. Or it may be true that you had an unfortunate childhood that left you with many emotional baggages that make life harder now. But regardless, you are responsible for moving toward your goals and either overcome or work around those limitations. In psychology there is a concept called “locus of control”. It measures how much people feel they have control over their own lives. People with an external locus of control are those who believe things happen to them. People with an internal locus of control are those who believe they can make things happen. Having an internal locus of control is associated with greater motivation and drive and higher resiliency in the face of adversity. (This why an internal locus of control is highly correlated with entrepreneurship). Having an external locus of control is associated with higher anxiety and greater susceptibility to depression. Extreme self-responsibility is a practice for shifting one’s locus of control inward. Of course, I’d be remiss if I didn’t point out that this philosophy runs in total opposition to the currently prevalent culture of victimhood. Instead of raising responsible, high self-esteem kids that trust their own competence in life, so many schools and universities are running in the direction of protecting everyone against the most minute slight. This aversion to anything that may be remotely unpleasant eliminates any sense of self-responsibility, and it raises impotent adults who are taught they’re unequipped to face the world as it is. In this way, victimhood culture worsens the lives of the very people it feigns compassion for. But, let us put our own house in order first. Extreme self-responsibility is something I had lost focus on for a long time, and I wanted to write about it as a refresher. I’m trying to put a renewed focus on this going forward.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meditation Retreat Recap</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/01/06/meditation-retreat-recap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meditation Retreat Recap" /><published>2018-01-06T14:17:15-08:00</published><updated>2018-01-06T14:17:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/01/06/meditation-retreat-recap</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2018/01/06/meditation-retreat-recap.html">&lt;p&gt;A month ago, I took an early morning Greyhound bus from Vancouver to Merritt to attend a 10-day meditation programme. I think when I look back, I will see this as one of the most profound experiences of my life. It was hard and gruelling, and I was apprehensive leading up to it, but I’m so glad that I went for it. Here, I will try to provide an overview/summary of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt; 


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt;: It&amp;rsquo;s impossible for me for convey the experience of meditation through a blog post and I&amp;rsquo;m not going to try.  In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ve written about some of my takeaways from the experience. It&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that ALL of the takeaways discussed here are &lt;em&gt;besides&lt;/em&gt; the central point of the retreat, which is the practice of meditation. In other words, what I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed here were the byproducts &lt;em&gt;for me at the time I took the course&lt;/em&gt;. Most important takeway of all is that the practice of meditation can lead to many such insights (and probably much more profound ones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why meditate?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I initially got into meditation as a stress management technique. One night when I was 28, I found myself in the office, alone, at 8 PM. I had just released a buggy version of our app, and it was causing issues on our customers’ phones. I had no idea what had gone wrong. As I was pouring over pages and pages of log data to detect the issue, I suddenly became cognizant of the sharp pains I was experiencing in my chest. My next thought was that since the office building is now empty, if I have a heart attack, nobody will find me until the next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had heard many guests on The Tim Ferriss Podcast talk about their meditation practice, so in 2017, I made it a new years’ resolution to establish a regular meditation practice, to be able to gain better control over my stress response. I stuck to a routine of doing 5-minutes/day, but I knew I did not understand what meditation really was, so I signed up for the retreat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that the promise of meditation is much loftier than simple “stress management”. Meditation is the practice by which one can end one’s suffering. I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;http://hirad.ca/blog/2016/08/06/on-worries-and-anxieties/&quot;&gt;written&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://hirad.ca/blog/2016/08/14/hardship-and-loss&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; about my philosophy of handling setbacks and unhappiness. This philosophy revolves around the acceptance of what is and being content with all things — desirable or undesirable — that are outside of one’s control. Even the subtitle of this blog (“making the map match the territory”) is about my quest to see the world &lt;em&gt;as it is&lt;/em&gt;, not as I want it to be. I’ve learned these lessons from stoic writings from Ancient Rome, and I’ve heard them echoed by Lao Tzu in &lt;em&gt;Tao Te Ching&lt;/em&gt;. As I’ve learned now, Buddhist thinking follows a similar theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while Lao Tzu and the Roman stoics were very clear about the end goal (building a strong mind), they were less clear about the path to get there. Vipassana meditation is, according to its practitioners, the Buddha’s method. And by training the mind, it promises to end all suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So tell me about the retreat!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meditation centre I attended is called Dhamma Surabhi, a 20-minute drive outside of Merritt. The main building is a square structure with a courtyard in the middle. On one end of the square is a large meditation hall, on the other end, there is a dining hall. The corridors connecting the two contain the rooms and bathrooms for the students, one side for men, the other for women. There is complete gender segregation for the duration of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start, the students are asked to commit to the following moral code for the duration of the course:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will abstain from killing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will abstain from stealing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will abstain from all sexual activity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will abstain from wrong speech&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will abstain from all intoxicants&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These precepts are interpreted rather broadly. The food at the retreat is all vegetarian because eating meat would violate the first precept — you’re supporting killing. And since it’s impossible for people to communicate with pure truth, students must observe “Noble Silence” for the duration of the course. This means no talking, no gestures, and no eye contact. There is a designated manager for men and women and students can raise any concerns with them if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you check-in, you&amp;rsquo;re asked to hand over your phone and any other electronic devices, plus any reading or writing material. Journalling, note-taking, and reading are all forbidden. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day of the course follows a timetable that you&amp;rsquo;re given on Day 0:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4:00 AM: Wake up bell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4:30 AM - 6:30 AM: Meditation in your room or in the hall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6:30 AM - 8:00 AM: Breakfast break (but breakfast is only served in the first 45 minutes).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:00 AM - 9:00 AM: Group meditation in the hall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:00 AM - 11:00 AM: Meditate in the hall or in your room, according to the teacher&amp;rsquo;s instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:00 AM - 1:00 PM: Lunch break (but lunch is only served in the first 45 minutes).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:00 PM - 2:00 PM: Meditate in the hall or in your room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:00 PM - 3:00 PM: Group meditation in the hall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:00 PM - 5:00 PM: Meditate in the hall or in your room, according to the teacher&amp;rsquo;s instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5:00 PM - 6:00 PM: Tea break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6:00 PM - 7:00 PM: Group meditation in the hall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:00 PM - 8:15 PM: The day&amp;rsquo;s discourse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:15 PM - 9:00 PM: Group meditation in the hall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:00 PM - 9:30 PM: Students can stay in the hall and ask questions from the assistant teacher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 PM: Lights out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There are several things you might notice from the above schedule:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are 11 hours and 45 minutes of meditation time everyday. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t leave time for much else, which is just fine, because there isn&amp;rsquo;t much else you could do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no dinner. During the tea break, new students (those who are doing their first 10-day course) get fruits in addition to tea. Old students get nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Food is served in short windows. Part of the reason for this is that the whole operation is run by few volunteers (at a time), and running the kitchen is difficult. In fact, this was one of the most impressive things I learned about the &lt;a href=&quot;www.dhamma.org&quot;&gt;organization&lt;/a&gt; that runs these courses: they have approx. 170 centres in over 90 countries and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; run by volunteers using donations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The break times are the only times you have for doing personal things you need to do, such as showering. And physical activity? You can go outside for a walk but the course boundary is a pretty limited area. You can&amp;rsquo;t run, as that might disturb the peace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Ok, what did you learn?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 10-day course is almost exclusively focused on learning a technique of meditation called Vipassana. I was very impressed by how laser-focused every aspect of the programme was on the technique and how hard they tried to avoid having it polluted by anything else. As you can see from the timetable, the daily discourses were the only time we were not either practicing meditation or taking time for some manner of bodily function (sleep, eating, or cleaning). The daily discourses did delve into philosophy and psychology – essentially covering the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; of the technique – but even they repeatedly put the utmost importance on the practice and shunned &amp;ldquo;playing intellectual games&amp;rdquo;. The discourse was given only as it was necessary to frame what the technique is and how it helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, Vipassana is a meditation that teaches you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to focus your mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to feel, at an experiential level, that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_too_shall_pass&quot;&gt;all things are changing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to be equanimous to things one does not have control over, thus putting an end to craving and aversion - the two sources of unhappiness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By constantly training the mind on the impermanence of things, one begins to break the uncontrollable cycles of craving and aversion and learns to accept reality as it is, not as one wants it to be. This is the meaning of &amp;ldquo;Vipassana&amp;rdquo; – seeing reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a very brief summary of the technique. As I mentioned, the technique was the most important thing and the thing we spent 11 hours on every day. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to do it justice in a blog post. If you want to learn how to meditate, I suggest you do the 10-day course. If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to do that, download an app, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.10percenthappier.com&quot;&gt;10% Happier&lt;/a&gt; and get started with a few minutes per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I will talk about now are my takeaways &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of the technique (but facilitated by the heightened powers of observation/awareness that the technique cultivates).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;The Silence&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I told people I was going to be silent for 10 days, they were shocked. Most thought of not being able to talk as some kind of unbearable torture. I can emphatically say that the silence is the &lt;em&gt;easiest&lt;/em&gt; part of the experience. Two days into the programme, I realized that I had not noticed any silence at all – there was plenty of chatter in my head to keep me busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the third night, my mind was starting to slow down and break out of its normal patterns of constantly generating thoughts. I went outside for a walk one evening, and sky was clear. I got to see the stars and I could see the clouds of the Milky Way. There aren&amp;rsquo;t too many things I get excited about. That was the most excited I&amp;rsquo;ve been in a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recalled a story I&amp;rsquo;d heard recently about a couple who met while each one was living in a remote cabin in the woods in northern BC, and they raised a family there for some time – far from the nearest town. After I&amp;rsquo;d heard this story, I found myself thinking about it repeatedly. It sounds insane. And yet so appealing. The constant barage of stimulii we live with – and are often unaware of – are constantly giving us fuel for worry and stress. Silence gives us space and peace. To experience this kind of living is something I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about with my friends for a long time, but over the last several years, I have increasingly deprived myself of it, for various invalid excuses. This is something I&amp;rsquo;ll be thinking about for some time and changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Elimination of all distractions&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By Day 5 of the course, I was seeing some real improvements in my ability to focus. I was getting acquainted with the silence and had starting untying some metaphorical knots I had recently created in my own mind. I was gaining clarity on where some of my recent struggles had originated and how I had contributed to them. I felt like I was having new epiphanies and insights every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I was learning this cool new technique, and I was learning about its origin: the story of the Buddha, Buddhist philosophy, and a little bit about the history of India – all topics I knew nothing about previously. As I said above, the utmost importance was placed on the techniques, and all of these topics were broached only as necessary to frame the technique. But they whet my apetite to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m having epiphanies and ideas, I typically like to write them down so I don&amp;rsquo;t forget. I like to discuss them with others. One way or another, I want to dwell on them.  I could not do that during the retreat, and this was hard and irritating. Similarly, when I get curious about any topic, I love the power of pulling out my phone and instantly learning more about it. I could not do this during the retreat. This was also irritating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent some time living with these frustrations. Then I had a new realization about how dumb these frustrations were. Everything about the format of this course is meant to be laser-focused on teaching these methods of meditation. The ban on journaling and internet access is meant precisely to keep the monkey minds of people like me from wandering off the goal. I had committed to 10 days of intense meditation practice. Now, instead of &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; the practice, I wanted to look up the history of India 3000 years ago or write down my thoughts about the last thing I was upset about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was madness, and it took me a while to realize because these behaviours seem so innocuous and are so ingrained. I realized that there are countless distractions that pop up in my mind that I&amp;rsquo;m totally aloof to. How much are these hurting the things I really want to accomplish? How much would we gain if we could eliminate these distractions that are being hurled at us more often?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since returning from the retreat, I&amp;rsquo;ve often caught myself in total distraction. I love the impact that our modern electronics have had on our lives, but there&amp;rsquo;s a serious downside that we need to learn to manage as well. Almost every time I take my phone out of my pocket, it is out of some unconscious habit that distracts me from what&amp;rsquo;s happening here and now. I love the fact that I can do so much with my phone – that so much knowledge is immediately available to me. But I realized that I have my mouth on a fire hose, trying to drink. This behaviour needs to be tamed. Since this technology is available to us now, we need a cultural shift in learning how to manage it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as I spent more time in &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; after the retreat, my ability to block out these distractions and focus my mind has dwindled rapidly. Only regular practice can make this a lasting gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Side note: I wrote a part of this blog post on a flight from Vancouver to Paris. I realized that flights are one area where I had already discovered the beauty of eliminating these distractions. On a flight, there is nothing to do. You can sit, sleep, work (if you work on a computer), read, or watch movies. This year when I was flying a lot, I started resisting the temptation of the in-flight entertainment system. Now, being on planes is some of my most productive time!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Compassion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Persian religion of Zarathushthrianism has a maxim: &lt;em&gt;Good thoughts, good words, good deeds&lt;/em&gt;. They&amp;rsquo;re put in that specific order, presumably because each depends on the one before. Similarly, in Vipassana great importance is placed on purity of thought. If the thoughts are not good, the actions can&amp;rsquo;t be, and if the actions are not good, according to Buddhist beliefs, one cannot progress on the path to &amp;ldquo;enlightenment&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultivating compassion is an important aspect of ridding one&amp;rsquo;s mind of &amp;ldquo;impurities&amp;rdquo;. The reason for this can start from a selfish place – the uncompassionate thoughts cause misery for oneself before they affect anyone else. It is also the end goal. Once you &amp;ldquo;reach enlightenment&amp;rdquo; and see the world as it is, your sense of self – as a separate thing from other beings – melts away, and you&amp;rsquo;re compelled to try to quell suffering whereever you find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the theory, and whether it&amp;rsquo;s true or not is not that important. The part that I bought into completely is the notion that being more compassionate makes one happier. It&amp;rsquo;s a win-win that I find hard to argue with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the duration of the course, I observed my inner talk shifting toward being more and more compassionate. Maybe this was the result of having bought into the above idea or maybe it was a product of meditating a lot. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, I like to be judgemental of people if for no other reason than self-amusement. When I started the course, even though it was impossible to communicate with the other students, I found myself having judgemental thoughts toward them. For exampe, I would watch people struggle with sitting on the floor. They were building elaborate monuments out of pillows and foams to make themselves more comfortable and they&amp;rsquo;d &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; not be able to sit still without constant shuffling. One of my roommates, who had clearly smoked a few too many joints in his day, slept through the first 5 days of the programme. This was annoying because it meant I could never meditate in the room because he&amp;rsquo;d be snoring in it. I found myself thinking: &amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t they kick him out if he&amp;rsquo;s just sleeping all the time!?&amp;rdquo;. There was a woman who was constantly coughing in the meditation hall. The cough was clearly psychosomatic. In fact, I had split a taxi with her on our way to the centre. During the 20 minute taxi ride (and during the social time at the end of the course) she never coughed once. Her incessant fake-coughing in the meditation hall also made me think: &amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t they kick her out!?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next 9 days, through no direct effort, I observed my inner-dialogue shift to a more compassionate version: I would feel bad about the people who were constantly shuffling pillows – clearly they were very uncomfortable with this style of sitting; I would think the fact that my pothead roommate was actually sticking around for the whole gruelling 10 days was pretty impressive; and I would feel bad for the fake-cougher – clearly she was living with a lack of self-awareness that surely must hurt her in her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By Day 8, the transformation of my inner-dialogue was very noticeable and I started worrying that this progress would be undone the minute I left the sanguine confines of the retreat. This has, indeed, occurred, but less than I was fearing. Like the ability to focus the mind, regular practice is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6&gt;Priya&amp;rsquo;s Misery&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fake-cougher was an Indian woman, named Priya. At the end of Day 9, just when I was being concerned about losing my progress in awareness and compassionate thought after the retreat, she gave me the perfect opportunity to see how what I learned applies in &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the question period, she approached the assistant teacher and (with a distressed voice) started asking an ambiguous question involving past lives and future lives. If you know me, you know that I have a very sensitive Bullshit-o-meter, and any serious talk of reincarnation triggers it, and here we had reincarnation being discussed seriously. I was annoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assistant teacher tried to get clarification. Priya finally said: &amp;ldquo;In my country, they say that you live 840,000 lives before being born as a human - because they counted the species.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inner dialogue: &amp;ldquo;Excuse me? The year is 2017, we&amp;rsquo;ve put men on the moon but we still can&amp;rsquo;t find all the species on Earth, and you think some asshole in India from 5000 years ago &lt;em&gt;counted&lt;/em&gt; all the species to know how long it takes to be &lt;em&gt;reincarnated&lt;/em&gt; as a human!? And it’s 840,000 round, huh? Not 845,238, just 840,000 - how fucking convenient!&amp;rdquo; Bullshit-o-meter was really going off now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priya continued (and I&amp;rsquo;m paraphrasing): &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve done this course two times now, and I just wanna know what happens to the work I&amp;rsquo;ve done here, because you know, I&amp;rsquo;m so tired of this cycle – I just want it to end.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inner dialogue: &amp;ldquo;YOU ARE WHAT? BITCH, DO YOU &lt;em&gt;REMEMBER&lt;/em&gt; HAVING DONE THE WORK FOR ALL THOSE 840,000 PAST LIVES? HOW INSANE ARE YOU!? WHY IS EVERYONE LOOKING AT THIS LIKE IT&amp;rsquo;S A SERIOUS DISCUSSION?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assistant teacher, at a loss, said: &amp;ldquo;You know, I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you what will happen in a future life, but I can tell you that this practice makes me happier today. Can you take that? Just be happy with that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Priya: &amp;ldquo;Yes. Thank you. You know, I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually want you to answer this question. But it&amp;rsquo;s such a big problem for me that I had to put the question out there, so maybe the universe will give me the answer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bullshit-o-meter was off the charts. Firstly, this woman believes in reincarnation with an absurd specificity about its mechanism; secondly, her insanity is so deep that she &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; tired of having been reincarnated so many times, making her desperate to end the cycle; and third, she hopes to be saved by the law of attraction, which is one of the most despicable and idiotic pseudo-religious quackery to have gained traction in my lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I was fuming. As I left the hall, I knew two things: any sense of compassion had gone out the window, and that this was my perfect opportunity to practice what I had learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried to find a more compassionate framing. Who was I angry at? I didn&amp;rsquo;t know. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t possibly have been angry at Priya. She hadn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;done&lt;/em&gt; anything. If anything, I should feel bad for her – she&amp;rsquo;s clearly suffering and in emotional distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I laid in bed, I tried to meditate. It didn&amp;rsquo;t do anything to remove the anger and agitation but it did give me an opportunity to step outside of the normal thought loops that one gets stuck in during anger. I noticed that I was so agitated that I had gotten chest pains. Then I remembered a Buddhist parable I had heard a few days earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day an angry young man lashed out at the Buddha. &amp;ldquo;When the man had finished his abuse, the Buddha asked him, saying: &amp;lsquo;Son, if a man declined to accept a present made to him, to whom would it belong?&amp;rsquo; And he answered: &amp;lsquo;In that case it would belong to the man who offered it.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;My son,&amp;rsquo; said the Buddha, &amp;lsquo;thou hast railed at me, but I decline to accept thy abuse, and request thee to keep it thyself. Will it not be a source of misery to thee? As the echo belongs to the sound, and the shadow to the substance, so misery will overtake the evil-doer without fail.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sacred-texts.com/bud/btg/btg58.htm&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that Priya had not tried to give me a gift of misery – I had forcibly yanked it away from her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation didn&amp;rsquo;t eliminate my anger, but it did open the opportunity for me to learn from it, and to observe how helpless I was as thoughts I had no control over emerged and overwhelmed my rational faculties. When I discussed this episode with the assistant teacher, he said I had the correct approach, and as I do this again and again, I will learn to notice and step outside of the anger earlier and earlier, until eventually, it simply ceases to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Views on Religion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be shocked to hear that I have&amp;rsquo;t been the biggest fan of religion. Over the years, when I would criticize various religions, people would try to defend them with really bad and weak arguments. Over the last 1-2 years, however, I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve been &amp;ldquo;deriving&amp;rdquo; religion for myself from first principles – finding rationale for various religious practices that make sense to me. This meditation retreat certainly accelerated that project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what was discussed during the course was about concepts I already knew and bought into. I realized, however, that these concepts were not of much use when I would hit real obstacles in life. I would always get overwhelmed by an emotional response and I would forget the principles by which I &lt;em&gt;believed&lt;/em&gt; I should handle obstacles. I realized that there is a lot of value in having a group of people who all share a mental model of the world to get together periodically and have a &amp;ldquo;sermon&amp;rdquo; on the same concepts they already believe. There is value in this repetition/reinforcement because it&amp;rsquo;s so difficult to remember the big picture when the going gets tough. I realized this is basically the practice of going to church every Sunday or doing Friday prayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this reinforcement practice is predicated on the underlying philosophy being sound/helpful, which I would argue is not the case with most sects. However, the practice is useful and we should not discard it due to its common application to poor ideologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, I spent a lot of time reflecting on the ways my thought patterns had created misery for me, and the ways in which awareness of these thought-patterns could help remedy the situation. As if suddenly struck by lightening, I understood Jordan Peterson&amp;rsquo;s view on religion and &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;. This was a stance of his that I could never understand or support before (you can listen to a gruelling conversation between him and Sam Harris on &amp;ldquo;What is truth&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samharris.org/podcast/item/what-is-true&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). My rephrasing (or perhaps, misinterpretation) of his stance makes much more sense to me than any articulation I&amp;rsquo;ve heard from him, and it is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion is true and science is true. They are both &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; at the same time. So how do we explain the contradictions between them? Jordan Peterson would say there mustn&amp;rsquo;t be a contradiction if we understand what these truths are, which he claims neither the religious nor science-oriented do. Religion is true in the domain of human psychology, science is true in the domain of objective reality. In other words, &lt;em&gt;a &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; belongs to a domain, and what is true in one domain may not necessarily &amp;ldquo;map&amp;rdquo; to another domain&lt;/em&gt;. So when Jordan Peterson talks about the bible, he has a very specific interpretation of, say, the story of genesis that pertains to certain facts of human experience and behaviour (with themes around jealousy, greed, etc). His interpretations of the bible always sounded good to me, but the question in my mind has always been: &amp;ldquo;But why &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; interpretation and not another one?&amp;rdquo; Well, I feel like I understand this now. If you view religion as a set of truths in the domain of human behaviour, then you must interpret it in a way that makes sense in that domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, to me, sounds like a way to have our cake and eat it too. We can take the benefits of religious belief and practice and leave its harms by the door, &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; we understand the domain in which religion operates. I don&amp;rsquo;t see this being a very scalable or realisitic path, but at an individual level, it is helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meditation retreat was an arduous experience. By Day 5, the static routine and 2-meal-per-day regimen was starting to wear me out. While I never thought about quitting, I did start thinking: &amp;ldquo;Ok, I&amp;rsquo;ve already learned some things. Ten days is really too long.&amp;rdquo; Throughout Days 6 and 7, I felt like I was still learning new things, but I was counting the hours and waiting for Day 10 to arrive. By Day 8, however, things changed, and I started realizing that the 10-day format was really &lt;em&gt;just right&lt;/em&gt; and that everyday I was learning more and more. I started worrying that ten days were not enough, and that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to retain everything I&amp;rsquo;d learned. They claim that this 10-day format was exactly how the Buddha taught Vipassana to &amp;ldquo;householders&amp;rdquo; (ie. laymen, not monks). Whether or not that&amp;rsquo;s true, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly been around for long enough that, in my opinion, it is perfect. I could not think of one way in which the course could be improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly enough, I found starting the course much easier than ending it. When Noble Silence ended, the sudden rush of noise all around me was overwhelming and unpleasant. And when I entered the city, with my hightened awareness and increased sensitivity to stimuli, my body felt like that of a scared animal. The first night, when I tried to meditate at home, I could feel subtle trembling all over my body. It was uncomfortable (and I tried to remember that it&amp;rsquo;s impermanent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the only measure of whether this experience was worthwhile or not is in its long term impact, and it can only have this impact with regular practice. They recommend that practitioners should do at least one hour of meditation in the morning and one hour in the evening. I thought that was an excessive prescription, but having done only one hour for a few weeks now, I see that the two hours is actually a minimum. I will now need to re-evaluate some priorities to ensure I get sufficient practice, and I hope I can do one retreat every year.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A month ago, I took an early morning Greyhound bus from Vancouver to Merritt to attend a 10-day meditation programme. I think when I look back, I will see this as one of the most profound experiences of my life. It was hard and gruelling, and I was apprehensive leading up to it, but I’m so glad that I went for it. Here, I will try to provide an overview/summary of the experience. Caveat: It&amp;rsquo;s impossible for me for convey the experience of meditation through a blog post and I&amp;rsquo;m not going to try. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ve written about some of my takeaways from the experience. It&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that ALL of the takeaways discussed here are besides the central point of the retreat, which is the practice of meditation. In other words, what I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed here were the byproducts for me at the time I took the course. Most important takeway of all is that the practice of meditation can lead to many such insights (and probably much more profound ones). Background Why meditate? I initially got into meditation as a stress management technique. One night when I was 28, I found myself in the office, alone, at 8 PM. I had just released a buggy version of our app, and it was causing issues on our customers’ phones. I had no idea what had gone wrong. As I was pouring over pages and pages of log data to detect the issue, I suddenly became cognizant of the sharp pains I was experiencing in my chest. My next thought was that since the office building is now empty, if I have a heart attack, nobody will find me until the next morning. I had heard many guests on The Tim Ferriss Podcast talk about their meditation practice, so in 2017, I made it a new years’ resolution to establish a regular meditation practice, to be able to gain better control over my stress response. I stuck to a routine of doing 5-minutes/day, but I knew I did not understand what meditation really was, so I signed up for the retreat. Now, I know that the promise of meditation is much loftier than simple “stress management”. Meditation is the practice by which one can end one’s suffering. I’ve written before about my philosophy of handling setbacks and unhappiness. This philosophy revolves around the acceptance of what is and being content with all things — desirable or undesirable — that are outside of one’s control. Even the subtitle of this blog (“making the map match the territory”) is about my quest to see the world as it is, not as I want it to be. I’ve learned these lessons from stoic writings from Ancient Rome, and I’ve heard them echoed by Lao Tzu in Tao Te Ching. As I’ve learned now, Buddhist thinking follows a similar theme. However, while Lao Tzu and the Roman stoics were very clear about the end goal (building a strong mind), they were less clear about the path to get there. Vipassana meditation is, according to its practitioners, the Buddha’s method. And by training the mind, it promises to end all suffering. So tell me about the retreat! The meditation centre I attended is called Dhamma Surabhi, a 20-minute drive outside of Merritt. The main building is a square structure with a courtyard in the middle. On one end of the square is a large meditation hall, on the other end, there is a dining hall. The corridors connecting the two contain the rooms and bathrooms for the students, one side for men, the other for women. There is complete gender segregation for the duration of the course. At the start, the students are asked to commit to the following moral code for the duration of the course: I will abstain from killing I will abstain from stealing I will abstain from all sexual activity I will abstain from wrong speech I will abstain from all intoxicants These precepts are interpreted rather broadly. The food at the retreat is all vegetarian because eating meat would violate the first precept — you’re supporting killing. And since it’s impossible for people to communicate with pure truth, students must observe “Noble Silence” for the duration of the course. This means no talking, no gestures, and no eye contact. There is a designated manager for men and women and students can raise any concerns with them if necessary. When you check-in, you&amp;rsquo;re asked to hand over your phone and any other electronic devices, plus any reading or writing material. Journalling, note-taking, and reading are all forbidden. More on that later. Every day of the course follows a timetable that you&amp;rsquo;re given on Day 0: 4:00 AM: Wake up bell. 4:30 AM - 6:30 AM: Meditation in your room or in the hall. 6:30 AM - 8:00 AM: Breakfast break (but breakfast is only served in the first 45 minutes). 8:00 AM - 9:00 AM: Group meditation in the hall. 9:00 AM - 11:00 AM: Meditate in the hall or in your room, according to the teacher&amp;rsquo;s instructions. 11:00 AM - 1:00 PM: Lunch break (but lunch is only served in the first 45 minutes). 1:00 PM - 2:00 PM: Meditate in the hall or in your room. 2:00 PM - 3:00 PM: Group meditation in the hall. 3:00 PM - 5:00 PM: Meditate in the hall or in your room, according to the teacher&amp;rsquo;s instructions. 5:00 PM - 6:00 PM: Tea break. 6:00 PM - 7:00 PM: Group meditation in the hall. 7:00 PM - 8:15 PM: The day&amp;rsquo;s discourse. 8:15 PM - 9:00 PM: Group meditation in the hall. 9:00 PM - 9:30 PM: Students can stay in the hall and ask questions from the assistant teacher. 10:00 PM: Lights out. There are several things you might notice from the above schedule: There are 11 hours and 45 minutes of meditation time everyday. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t leave time for much else, which is just fine, because there isn&amp;rsquo;t much else you could do. There&amp;rsquo;s no dinner. During the tea break, new students (those who are doing their first 10-day course) get fruits in addition to tea. Old students get nothing. Food is served in short windows. Part of the reason for this is that the whole operation is run by few volunteers (at a time), and running the kitchen is difficult. In fact, this was one of the most impressive things I learned about the organization that runs these courses: they have approx. 170 centres in over 90 countries and it&amp;rsquo;s all run by volunteers using donations. The break times are the only times you have for doing personal things you need to do, such as showering. And physical activity? You can go outside for a walk but the course boundary is a pretty limited area. You can&amp;rsquo;t run, as that might disturb the peace. Ok, what did you learn? The 10-day course is almost exclusively focused on learning a technique of meditation called Vipassana. I was very impressed by how laser-focused every aspect of the programme was on the technique and how hard they tried to avoid having it polluted by anything else. As you can see from the timetable, the daily discourses were the only time we were not either practicing meditation or taking time for some manner of bodily function (sleep, eating, or cleaning). The daily discourses did delve into philosophy and psychology – essentially covering the why of the technique – but even they repeatedly put the utmost importance on the practice and shunned &amp;ldquo;playing intellectual games&amp;rdquo;. The discourse was given only as it was necessary to frame what the technique is and how it helps. In short, Vipassana is a meditation that teaches you: The ability to focus your mind. The ability to feel, at an experiential level, that all things are changing. The ability to be equanimous to things one does not have control over, thus putting an end to craving and aversion - the two sources of unhappiness. By constantly training the mind on the impermanence of things, one begins to break the uncontrollable cycles of craving and aversion and learns to accept reality as it is, not as one wants it to be. This is the meaning of &amp;ldquo;Vipassana&amp;rdquo; – seeing reality. That&amp;rsquo;s a very brief summary of the technique. As I mentioned, the technique was the most important thing and the thing we spent 11 hours on every day. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to do it justice in a blog post. If you want to learn how to meditate, I suggest you do the 10-day course. If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to do that, download an app, like 10% Happier and get started with a few minutes per day. What I will talk about now are my takeaways outside of the technique (but facilitated by the heightened powers of observation/awareness that the technique cultivates). The Silence When I told people I was going to be silent for 10 days, they were shocked. Most thought of not being able to talk as some kind of unbearable torture. I can emphatically say that the silence is the easiest part of the experience. Two days into the programme, I realized that I had not noticed any silence at all – there was plenty of chatter in my head to keep me busy. On the third night, my mind was starting to slow down and break out of its normal patterns of constantly generating thoughts. I went outside for a walk one evening, and sky was clear. I got to see the stars and I could see the clouds of the Milky Way. There aren&amp;rsquo;t too many things I get excited about. That was the most excited I&amp;rsquo;ve been in a long time. I recalled a story I&amp;rsquo;d heard recently about a couple who met while each one was living in a remote cabin in the woods in northern BC, and they raised a family there for some time – far from the nearest town. After I&amp;rsquo;d heard this story, I found myself thinking about it repeatedly. It sounds insane. And yet so appealing. The constant barage of stimulii we live with – and are often unaware of – are constantly giving us fuel for worry and stress. Silence gives us space and peace. To experience this kind of living is something I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about with my friends for a long time, but over the last several years, I have increasingly deprived myself of it, for various invalid excuses. This is something I&amp;rsquo;ll be thinking about for some time and changing. Elimination of all distractions By Day 5 of the course, I was seeing some real improvements in my ability to focus. I was getting acquainted with the silence and had starting untying some metaphorical knots I had recently created in my own mind. I was gaining clarity on where some of my recent struggles had originated and how I had contributed to them. I felt like I was having new epiphanies and insights every day. At the same time, I was learning this cool new technique, and I was learning about its origin: the story of the Buddha, Buddhist philosophy, and a little bit about the history of India – all topics I knew nothing about previously. As I said above, the utmost importance was placed on the techniques, and all of these topics were broached only as necessary to frame the technique. But they whet my apetite to learn more. When I&amp;rsquo;m having epiphanies and ideas, I typically like to write them down so I don&amp;rsquo;t forget. I like to discuss them with others. One way or another, I want to dwell on them. I could not do that during the retreat, and this was hard and irritating. Similarly, when I get curious about any topic, I love the power of pulling out my phone and instantly learning more about it. I could not do this during the retreat. This was also irritating. I spent some time living with these frustrations. Then I had a new realization about how dumb these frustrations were. Everything about the format of this course is meant to be laser-focused on teaching these methods of meditation. The ban on journaling and internet access is meant precisely to keep the monkey minds of people like me from wandering off the goal. I had committed to 10 days of intense meditation practice. Now, instead of doing the practice, I wanted to look up the history of India 3000 years ago or write down my thoughts about the last thing I was upset about. This was madness, and it took me a while to realize because these behaviours seem so innocuous and are so ingrained. I realized that there are countless distractions that pop up in my mind that I&amp;rsquo;m totally aloof to. How much are these hurting the things I really want to accomplish? How much would we gain if we could eliminate these distractions that are being hurled at us more often? Since returning from the retreat, I&amp;rsquo;ve often caught myself in total distraction. I love the impact that our modern electronics have had on our lives, but there&amp;rsquo;s a serious downside that we need to learn to manage as well. Almost every time I take my phone out of my pocket, it is out of some unconscious habit that distracts me from what&amp;rsquo;s happening here and now. I love the fact that I can do so much with my phone – that so much knowledge is immediately available to me. But I realized that I have my mouth on a fire hose, trying to drink. This behaviour needs to be tamed. Since this technology is available to us now, we need a cultural shift in learning how to manage it. Unfortunately, as I spent more time in &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; after the retreat, my ability to block out these distractions and focus my mind has dwindled rapidly. Only regular practice can make this a lasting gain. Side note: I wrote a part of this blog post on a flight from Vancouver to Paris. I realized that flights are one area where I had already discovered the beauty of eliminating these distractions. On a flight, there is nothing to do. You can sit, sleep, work (if you work on a computer), read, or watch movies. This year when I was flying a lot, I started resisting the temptation of the in-flight entertainment system. Now, being on planes is some of my most productive time! Compassion The Persian religion of Zarathushthrianism has a maxim: Good thoughts, good words, good deeds. They&amp;rsquo;re put in that specific order, presumably because each depends on the one before. Similarly, in Vipassana great importance is placed on purity of thought. If the thoughts are not good, the actions can&amp;rsquo;t be, and if the actions are not good, according to Buddhist beliefs, one cannot progress on the path to &amp;ldquo;enlightenment&amp;rdquo;. Cultivating compassion is an important aspect of ridding one&amp;rsquo;s mind of &amp;ldquo;impurities&amp;rdquo;. The reason for this can start from a selfish place – the uncompassionate thoughts cause misery for oneself before they affect anyone else. It is also the end goal. Once you &amp;ldquo;reach enlightenment&amp;rdquo; and see the world as it is, your sense of self – as a separate thing from other beings – melts away, and you&amp;rsquo;re compelled to try to quell suffering whereever you find it. This is the theory, and whether it&amp;rsquo;s true or not is not that important. The part that I bought into completely is the notion that being more compassionate makes one happier. It&amp;rsquo;s a win-win that I find hard to argue with. Over the duration of the course, I observed my inner talk shifting toward being more and more compassionate. Maybe this was the result of having bought into the above idea or maybe it was a product of meditating a lot. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure. Typically, I like to be judgemental of people if for no other reason than self-amusement. When I started the course, even though it was impossible to communicate with the other students, I found myself having judgemental thoughts toward them. For exampe, I would watch people struggle with sitting on the floor. They were building elaborate monuments out of pillows and foams to make themselves more comfortable and they&amp;rsquo;d still not be able to sit still without constant shuffling. One of my roommates, who had clearly smoked a few too many joints in his day, slept through the first 5 days of the programme. This was annoying because it meant I could never meditate in the room because he&amp;rsquo;d be snoring in it. I found myself thinking: &amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t they kick him out if he&amp;rsquo;s just sleeping all the time!?&amp;rdquo;. There was a woman who was constantly coughing in the meditation hall. The cough was clearly psychosomatic. In fact, I had split a taxi with her on our way to the centre. During the 20 minute taxi ride (and during the social time at the end of the course) she never coughed once. Her incessant fake-coughing in the meditation hall also made me think: &amp;ldquo;Why don&amp;rsquo;t they kick her out!?&amp;rdquo; Over the next 9 days, through no direct effort, I observed my inner-dialogue shift to a more compassionate version: I would feel bad about the people who were constantly shuffling pillows – clearly they were very uncomfortable with this style of sitting; I would think the fact that my pothead roommate was actually sticking around for the whole gruelling 10 days was pretty impressive; and I would feel bad for the fake-cougher – clearly she was living with a lack of self-awareness that surely must hurt her in her life. By Day 8, the transformation of my inner-dialogue was very noticeable and I started worrying that this progress would be undone the minute I left the sanguine confines of the retreat. This has, indeed, occurred, but less than I was fearing. Like the ability to focus the mind, regular practice is required. Priya&amp;rsquo;s Misery The fake-cougher was an Indian woman, named Priya. At the end of Day 9, just when I was being concerned about losing my progress in awareness and compassionate thought after the retreat, she gave me the perfect opportunity to see how what I learned applies in &amp;ldquo;real world&amp;rdquo; scenarios. During the question period, she approached the assistant teacher and (with a distressed voice) started asking an ambiguous question involving past lives and future lives. If you know me, you know that I have a very sensitive Bullshit-o-meter, and any serious talk of reincarnation triggers it, and here we had reincarnation being discussed seriously. I was annoyed. The assistant teacher tried to get clarification. Priya finally said: &amp;ldquo;In my country, they say that you live 840,000 lives before being born as a human - because they counted the species.&amp;rdquo; My inner dialogue: &amp;ldquo;Excuse me? The year is 2017, we&amp;rsquo;ve put men on the moon but we still can&amp;rsquo;t find all the species on Earth, and you think some asshole in India from 5000 years ago counted all the species to know how long it takes to be reincarnated as a human!? And it’s 840,000 round, huh? Not 845,238, just 840,000 - how fucking convenient!&amp;rdquo; Bullshit-o-meter was really going off now. Priya continued (and I&amp;rsquo;m paraphrasing): &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve done this course two times now, and I just wanna know what happens to the work I&amp;rsquo;ve done here, because you know, I&amp;rsquo;m so tired of this cycle – I just want it to end.&amp;rdquo; Inner dialogue: &amp;ldquo;YOU ARE WHAT? BITCH, DO YOU REMEMBER HAVING DONE THE WORK FOR ALL THOSE 840,000 PAST LIVES? HOW INSANE ARE YOU!? WHY IS EVERYONE LOOKING AT THIS LIKE IT&amp;rsquo;S A SERIOUS DISCUSSION?&amp;rdquo; The assistant teacher, at a loss, said: &amp;ldquo;You know, I can&amp;rsquo;t tell you what will happen in a future life, but I can tell you that this practice makes me happier today. Can you take that? Just be happy with that.&amp;rdquo; Priya: &amp;ldquo;Yes. Thank you. You know, I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually want you to answer this question. But it&amp;rsquo;s such a big problem for me that I had to put the question out there, so maybe the universe will give me the answer.&amp;rdquo; My bullshit-o-meter was off the charts. Firstly, this woman believes in reincarnation with an absurd specificity about its mechanism; secondly, her insanity is so deep that she feels tired of having been reincarnated so many times, making her desperate to end the cycle; and third, she hopes to be saved by the law of attraction, which is one of the most despicable and idiotic pseudo-religious quackery to have gained traction in my lifetime. At this point, I was fuming. As I left the hall, I knew two things: any sense of compassion had gone out the window, and that this was my perfect opportunity to practice what I had learned. I tried to find a more compassionate framing. Who was I angry at? I didn&amp;rsquo;t know. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t possibly have been angry at Priya. She hadn&amp;rsquo;t done anything. If anything, I should feel bad for her – she&amp;rsquo;s clearly suffering and in emotional distress. As I laid in bed, I tried to meditate. It didn&amp;rsquo;t do anything to remove the anger and agitation but it did give me an opportunity to step outside of the normal thought loops that one gets stuck in during anger. I noticed that I was so agitated that I had gotten chest pains. Then I remembered a Buddhist parable I had heard a few days earlier: One day an angry young man lashed out at the Buddha. &amp;ldquo;When the man had finished his abuse, the Buddha asked him, saying: &amp;lsquo;Son, if a man declined to accept a present made to him, to whom would it belong?&amp;rsquo; And he answered: &amp;lsquo;In that case it would belong to the man who offered it.&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;My son,&amp;rsquo; said the Buddha, &amp;lsquo;thou hast railed at me, but I decline to accept thy abuse, and request thee to keep it thyself. Will it not be a source of misery to thee? As the echo belongs to the sound, and the shadow to the substance, so misery will overtake the evil-doer without fail.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; (source) I realized that Priya had not tried to give me a gift of misery – I had forcibly yanked it away from her. Meditation didn&amp;rsquo;t eliminate my anger, but it did open the opportunity for me to learn from it, and to observe how helpless I was as thoughts I had no control over emerged and overwhelmed my rational faculties. When I discussed this episode with the assistant teacher, he said I had the correct approach, and as I do this again and again, I will learn to notice and step outside of the anger earlier and earlier, until eventually, it simply ceases to emerge. Views on Religion You may be shocked to hear that I have&amp;rsquo;t been the biggest fan of religion. Over the years, when I would criticize various religions, people would try to defend them with really bad and weak arguments. Over the last 1-2 years, however, I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve been &amp;ldquo;deriving&amp;rdquo; religion for myself from first principles – finding rationale for various religious practices that make sense to me. This meditation retreat certainly accelerated that project. Much of what was discussed during the course was about concepts I already knew and bought into. I realized, however, that these concepts were not of much use when I would hit real obstacles in life. I would always get overwhelmed by an emotional response and I would forget the principles by which I believed I should handle obstacles. I realized that there is a lot of value in having a group of people who all share a mental model of the world to get together periodically and have a &amp;ldquo;sermon&amp;rdquo; on the same concepts they already believe. There is value in this repetition/reinforcement because it&amp;rsquo;s so difficult to remember the big picture when the going gets tough. I realized this is basically the practice of going to church every Sunday or doing Friday prayers. Of course, this reinforcement practice is predicated on the underlying philosophy being sound/helpful, which I would argue is not the case with most sects. However, the practice is useful and we should not discard it due to its common application to poor ideologies. Throughout the course, I spent a lot of time reflecting on the ways my thought patterns had created misery for me, and the ways in which awareness of these thought-patterns could help remedy the situation. As if suddenly struck by lightening, I understood Jordan Peterson&amp;rsquo;s view on religion and &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;. This was a stance of his that I could never understand or support before (you can listen to a gruelling conversation between him and Sam Harris on &amp;ldquo;What is truth&amp;rdquo; here). My rephrasing (or perhaps, misinterpretation) of his stance makes much more sense to me than any articulation I&amp;rsquo;ve heard from him, and it is this: Religion is true and science is true. They are both &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; at the same time. So how do we explain the contradictions between them? Jordan Peterson would say there mustn&amp;rsquo;t be a contradiction if we understand what these truths are, which he claims neither the religious nor science-oriented do. Religion is true in the domain of human psychology, science is true in the domain of objective reality. In other words, a &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; belongs to a domain, and what is true in one domain may not necessarily &amp;ldquo;map&amp;rdquo; to another domain. So when Jordan Peterson talks about the bible, he has a very specific interpretation of, say, the story of genesis that pertains to certain facts of human experience and behaviour (with themes around jealousy, greed, etc). His interpretations of the bible always sounded good to me, but the question in my mind has always been: &amp;ldquo;But why that interpretation and not another one?&amp;rdquo; Well, I feel like I understand this now. If you view religion as a set of truths in the domain of human behaviour, then you must interpret it in a way that makes sense in that domain. This, to me, sounds like a way to have our cake and eat it too. We can take the benefits of religious belief and practice and leave its harms by the door, if we understand the domain in which religion operates. I don&amp;rsquo;t see this being a very scalable or realisitic path, but at an individual level, it is helpful. Conclusion The meditation retreat was an arduous experience. By Day 5, the static routine and 2-meal-per-day regimen was starting to wear me out. While I never thought about quitting, I did start thinking: &amp;ldquo;Ok, I&amp;rsquo;ve already learned some things. Ten days is really too long.&amp;rdquo; Throughout Days 6 and 7, I felt like I was still learning new things, but I was counting the hours and waiting for Day 10 to arrive. By Day 8, however, things changed, and I started realizing that the 10-day format was really just right and that everyday I was learning more and more. I started worrying that ten days were not enough, and that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to retain everything I&amp;rsquo;d learned. They claim that this 10-day format was exactly how the Buddha taught Vipassana to &amp;ldquo;householders&amp;rdquo; (ie. laymen, not monks). Whether or not that&amp;rsquo;s true, it&amp;rsquo;s certainly been around for long enough that, in my opinion, it is perfect. I could not think of one way in which the course could be improved. Surprisingly enough, I found starting the course much easier than ending it. When Noble Silence ended, the sudden rush of noise all around me was overwhelming and unpleasant. And when I entered the city, with my hightened awareness and increased sensitivity to stimuli, my body felt like that of a scared animal. The first night, when I tried to meditate at home, I could feel subtle trembling all over my body. It was uncomfortable (and I tried to remember that it&amp;rsquo;s impermanent). Of course, the only measure of whether this experience was worthwhile or not is in its long term impact, and it can only have this impact with regular practice. They recommend that practitioners should do at least one hour of meditation in the morning and one hour in the evening. I thought that was an excessive prescription, but having done only one hour for a few weeks now, I see that the two hours is actually a minimum. I will now need to re-evaluate some priorities to ensure I get sufficient practice, and I hope I can do one retreat every year.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cheap Chopsticks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/essays/2017/11/17/cheap-chopsticks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cheap Chopsticks" /><published>2017-11-17T10:51:12-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-17T10:51:12-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/essays/2017/11/17/cheap-chopsticks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/essays/2017/11/17/cheap-chopsticks.html">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/566/32161433225_df23507ee4_b.jpg&quot; width=512 height=339&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Poke Guy is an excellent little hole-in-the-wall in Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s Gastown district. It sells customizable dishes with rice, fish, veggies, and some delicious sauces. It&amp;rsquo;s high quality food – the kind of eating out that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to feel guilty about. I ordered a big dish with a little bit of everything, complete with a sprinkle of wasabi mayo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- More --&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you walk into The Poke Guy, you can tell it&amp;rsquo;s a well-thought-through business. Customers are moved, very quickly, from one end of the queue all the way to the cashier like parts on an assembly line. The displays look good, and their unusual pricing model can be easily gleaned by a glance at their menu. Whoever runs this place clearly put a lot of thought (and/or experience) into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They chose to use the cheapest kinds of chopsticks that are available. From a purely mathematical cost/benefit analysis, that&amp;rsquo;s not such a bad trade-off. Perhaps, they can pass those savings onto their customers. Maybe, after all the effort and thought that&amp;rsquo;s gone into the food and the process, having cheap chopsticks is a reasonable tradeoff. Who&amp;rsquo;d ever notice the meek chopstick?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I sat down to eat the food I had just ordered, I grabbed a pair of chopsticks that were available from a cup in front of me. As I applied force to the chopsticks to grasp the first bite, one of the chopsticks snapped in mid-air, flinging mayo-covered veggies on my face, my shirt, and my pants. The initial upset from an unfortunate event like this dissipates fairly quickly, but it does offer an opportunity for reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would the owners of The Poke Guy think that one (at least) of their customers having this experience is OK? If being in business required that every once in a while they take a bunch of saunce-covered food and fling it in someone&amp;rsquo;s face, would they still do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the answer is a resounding &amp;lsquo;no&amp;rsquo;. And yet, for some reason, we&amp;rsquo;re constantly OK with making these tradeoffs if the causal chain between our decision and the negative outcome for one of our customers gets long enough. Every time you decide to do shoddy work or to use cheap materials or to hire unreliable staff, you&amp;rsquo;re implicitly deciding that a shitty experience for your customers is OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m as big a fan of capitalism as anyone, but the pursuit of pure profits without a sense of a greater mission is precisely what gives capitalism a bad rap. Once these compromises permeate all of our day-to-day experiences (and they do), we become blind to them, and we accept them as inevitabilities. This acceptance, in turn, will lead us to perform our own duties in life more neglectfully and carelessly. It&amp;rsquo;s a vicious cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might sound trite to say this as a response to a broken chopstick, but it is exactly the triviality that makes this a worthy case study. Minute decisions a business makes can have a magnified impact on the world. We cannot seek praise for what we do that is already in our own self-interest. Virtue is only worthy of praise precisely when it poses a difficulty for the virtuous. If we believe in capitalism with mission and values, if – as so many silicon valley companies profess – we actually want to build businesses that change the world, then we must pursue the betterment of our customers' lives, not as a marketing strategy but as a sacred value and with religious fervour. Of course, profit and loss is an existential limitation that should be taken seriously by any rationally-thinking businessperson, but we can&amp;rsquo;t lose sight of the fact that it is an obstacle that we must overcome and not the goal itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the vast majority of those who love to hate capitalism do so precisely because of so many encounters with business entities that preach one thing but practice something else - businesses that try to project a false image. People may not be able to articulate this point exactly, but they feel it at an emotional level, and much like an inauthentic encounter with someone you know is a pathological liar, they feel disgust at these profit-seekers who have no greater sense of virtue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the beauty of capitalism is that we are, collectively, in control of this situation. If we decide that it is worthwhile to pay extra to businesses that pour their heart and soul in to their products and services, we can incentivize this behaviour. As customers, it is our duty to reward good behaviour, and as businesses, we need to realize that our impact in the world goes far beyond what can be captured on a spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about all this as I cleaned off stains of wasabi mayo from my clothes before heading back to the office. Luckily, there were no important meetings that day and stain-covered clothes were not a huge impediment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Poke Guy is an excellent little hole-in-the-wall in Vancouver&amp;rsquo;s Gastown district. It sells customizable dishes with rice, fish, veggies, and some delicious sauces. It&amp;rsquo;s high quality food – the kind of eating out that you don&amp;rsquo;t have to feel guilty about. I ordered a big dish with a little bit of everything, complete with a sprinkle of wasabi mayo. When you walk into The Poke Guy, you can tell it&amp;rsquo;s a well-thought-through business. Customers are moved, very quickly, from one end of the queue all the way to the cashier like parts on an assembly line. The displays look good, and their unusual pricing model can be easily gleaned by a glance at their menu. Whoever runs this place clearly put a lot of thought (and/or experience) into it. But&amp;hellip; They chose to use the cheapest kinds of chopsticks that are available. From a purely mathematical cost/benefit analysis, that&amp;rsquo;s not such a bad trade-off. Perhaps, they can pass those savings onto their customers. Maybe, after all the effort and thought that&amp;rsquo;s gone into the food and the process, having cheap chopsticks is a reasonable tradeoff. Who&amp;rsquo;d ever notice the meek chopstick? As I sat down to eat the food I had just ordered, I grabbed a pair of chopsticks that were available from a cup in front of me. As I applied force to the chopsticks to grasp the first bite, one of the chopsticks snapped in mid-air, flinging mayo-covered veggies on my face, my shirt, and my pants. The initial upset from an unfortunate event like this dissipates fairly quickly, but it does offer an opportunity for reflection. Would the owners of The Poke Guy think that one (at least) of their customers having this experience is OK? If being in business required that every once in a while they take a bunch of saunce-covered food and fling it in someone&amp;rsquo;s face, would they still do it? I think the answer is a resounding &amp;lsquo;no&amp;rsquo;. And yet, for some reason, we&amp;rsquo;re constantly OK with making these tradeoffs if the causal chain between our decision and the negative outcome for one of our customers gets long enough. Every time you decide to do shoddy work or to use cheap materials or to hire unreliable staff, you&amp;rsquo;re implicitly deciding that a shitty experience for your customers is OK. I&amp;rsquo;m as big a fan of capitalism as anyone, but the pursuit of pure profits without a sense of a greater mission is precisely what gives capitalism a bad rap. Once these compromises permeate all of our day-to-day experiences (and they do), we become blind to them, and we accept them as inevitabilities. This acceptance, in turn, will lead us to perform our own duties in life more neglectfully and carelessly. It&amp;rsquo;s a vicious cycle. It might sound trite to say this as a response to a broken chopstick, but it is exactly the triviality that makes this a worthy case study. Minute decisions a business makes can have a magnified impact on the world. We cannot seek praise for what we do that is already in our own self-interest. Virtue is only worthy of praise precisely when it poses a difficulty for the virtuous. If we believe in capitalism with mission and values, if – as so many silicon valley companies profess – we actually want to build businesses that change the world, then we must pursue the betterment of our customers' lives, not as a marketing strategy but as a sacred value and with religious fervour. Of course, profit and loss is an existential limitation that should be taken seriously by any rationally-thinking businessperson, but we can&amp;rsquo;t lose sight of the fact that it is an obstacle that we must overcome and not the goal itself. I suspect that the vast majority of those who love to hate capitalism do so precisely because of so many encounters with business entities that preach one thing but practice something else - businesses that try to project a false image. People may not be able to articulate this point exactly, but they feel it at an emotional level, and much like an inauthentic encounter with someone you know is a pathological liar, they feel disgust at these profit-seekers who have no greater sense of virtue. Of course, the beauty of capitalism is that we are, collectively, in control of this situation. If we decide that it is worthwhile to pay extra to businesses that pour their heart and soul in to their products and services, we can incentivize this behaviour. As customers, it is our duty to reward good behaviour, and as businesses, we need to realize that our impact in the world goes far beyond what can be captured on a spreadsheet. I thought about all this as I cleaned off stains of wasabi mayo from my clothes before heading back to the office. Luckily, there were no important meetings that day and stain-covered clothes were not a huge impediment.</summary></entry></feed>